<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An excellent and godly sermon most needefull for this time, wherein we liue in all securitie and sinne, to the great dishonour of God, and contempt of his holy word. Preached at Paules Crosse the xxvi. daye of October, an. 1578 by Laurence Chaderton Batcheler of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Chaderton, Laurence, 1536?-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853055</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 313:08, 878:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An excellent and godly sermon most needefull for this time, wherein we liue in all securitie and sinne, to the great dishonour of God, and contempt of his holy word. Preached at Paules Crosse the xxvi. daye of October, an. 1578 by Laurence Chaderton Batcheler of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Chaderton, Laurence, 1536?-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[116] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1578?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 4925 on reel 313.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A godly sermon preached at Paules crosse.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, A3r line 1 ends "flesh,".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H² .</note>
                  <note>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy imperfect; A1, title page, lacking.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 313 #8 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy, identified as STC 4925), and at reel 878 ø (Folger Shakespeare Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:1"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull <hi>Maſter Richard Martin,</hi> Warden of the Queenes Maieſties Mints, and Alderman of the Citie of London, Grace and peace from God the Father, through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue ſent vnto you, right worſhipfull, and dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in the Lord, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and my promiſe, the ſumme and effecte of my Sermon preached at Paules Croſſe: deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you to receiue it, as a moſt certaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of my vnfayned loue towardes you in Chriſt. For although it come from an olde friend and brother in the Lord: yet I ſend it vnto your worſhip for a Newe yeres gift, to teſtifie a newe increaſe of my Chriſtian loue towards you, &amp; ſo many as ſhal reade it, with purpoſe to liue according to the rule of ſound doctrine and godlines: And concerning you, of whoſe integritie I haue good experience, I perſwade my ſelfe that our moſt mercifull Father, by this meanes
<pb facs="tcp:18418:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> vvill vvorke in your heart, the plentifull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the giftes and invvard graces of that nevv man, vvhich is framed according to the Image of his dearely beloued ſonne Chriſt Ieſus. For as you haue bene moſt earneſt to haue in vvriting this doctrine: ſo I doubt not, but you vvill be moſt diligent in the practiſe thereof: for vvhich cauſe I commit it into your hands, to vſe to Gods glorie, the profit of his children, &amp; to your ovvne comfort. Grace, peace, and loue vvith faith, from God the Father, and from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt be vvith you novve and euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Cambridge,</dateline> 
               <signed>by your moſt louing friend, and brother in the Lord, <hi>Laurence Chaderton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S much reading is a wearines to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, ſo there is neither end nor profit, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many bookes. True wiſdome eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheweth both: but the folie of our time neuer ceaſeth to write, nether can be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with reading the new and variable inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of men. A fault amongſt wiſe Philoſophers much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, how much more ought it to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed of al learned Chriſtians? But vaine glory, &amp; deſire of popular fame in the writers, &amp; deſire of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre in the Printers, haue ſtuffed our Engliſh ſtudies with many ſuperfluous &amp; vnneceſſary books to the great hurt of many good wits, &amp; to the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctrine. A matter moſt neceſſary to be reformed by ſuch as haue receiued authority to this end, that neither our Church, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale ſhuld be hurt, but rather bettered by the writings of men. For my part, I wiſh with all my heart, that we had fewer bookes, &amp; greater ſkill in the old &amp; newe Teſtament of Chriſt, wherin are bequeathed vnto vs moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly &amp; precious Iewels, &amp; legacies of the immortal inheritance: to which moſt ſure word &amp; Teſtament, if we take heed as vnto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, we ſhalbe directed aright in the ſtrait way that leadeth to immortalitie &amp; happines. Now touching this my Sermon, if I did thinke (deare Chriſtian Reader) that it would quench in the mind of any, the deſire of hearing the Goſpell preached, &amp; not rather inflame their heart, both to hearing &amp; faithful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, I would rather haue buried it in perpetuall ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then committed it to writing. But being fully perſwaded, that by this meanes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord God in mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye wil bring into the minds of thoſe that heard me, a fruitfull reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his mighty working by the power of his ſpirit, at that preſent, to their ſingular comfort: I haue in ſome part ſatiſfied the earneſt, &amp; importunat ſute of many deare Chriſtians and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:3"/> who did both by letters &amp; word of mouth, after a ſort compel me to write it. The ſumme and effect of al I haue ſet downe, not in the ſame words I ſpake (for the Lord knoweth I neuer writ it and therfore could not) but in other, ſo plainly as I could for the capacity and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of al. I haue added thoſe things, whereof then I could not, partly for lacke of time, partly for other neceſſary occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, intreat. And albeit mine owne inabilitie in this kinde of writing, wherein I am altogether a ſtranger, and the feare of the ſeuere cenſure of the learned eloquent diuines, did greatly diſſwade me: yet my earneſt deſire both to leaue behind me ſome ſmal teſtimonie of my ſaith, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; religion: &amp; alſo to haue my iudgement tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching faith &amp; workes approued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh church, did as it were viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly carie me to this dutiful worke of loue. Now my harty deſire is, that this my labour may be acceptably receiued, &amp; louingly expounded of all, &amp; my prayer vnto God is &amp; ſhalbe, that euery one of vs, according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, may be inabled by his ſpirit, to hold faſt the ſound doctrine of pure religion, in life and in death, &amp; with al ioy of the holy Ghoſt ſincerely to practiſe the ſame, to the glory of Chriſt, &amp; the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Church. But let no man thinke, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reading of this can be half ſo effectual and profitable to him, as the hearing was, or might be. For it wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth the zeale of the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the attention of the hearer, the promiſe of God to the ordinary preaching of his word, the mighty &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward working of his holy ſpirit, &amp; many other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which the Lord worketh moſt mercifully by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his glorious Goſpel, which are not to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for by reading the written Sermons of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Neuertheleſſe I truſt that he will bleſſe the reading hereof, to the praiſe of his owne name, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his Church. To him therefore by Chriſt be al praiſe &amp; honour in the Church for euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Matthewe vij.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>21</bibl> Not euery one that ſaith vnto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen: but he that doth my Fathers wil which is in heauen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>22</bibl> Many will ſay to mee in that daye, Lord, Lord, haue we not by thy Name pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, and by thy Name caſt out deuils, &amp; by thy Name done many great works?</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>23</bibl> And then will I profeſſe to them, I neuer knewe you: depart from me ye that worke iniquitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe three ſhort verſes are a principall part of that heauenly ſermon,<note place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this text.</note> which our ſauiour Chriſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the mount vnto his own diſciples and the people. The ſumme and meaning hereof is, a dreadful declaration of the final deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and eternall condemnation of all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait and hypocritical profeſſors of Gods true Religion. For although in the former verſes Chriſt did particularly deſcribe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:18418:4"/> his auditorie falſe and diſſembling pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets by their fruits, to the end they might better know them:<note place="margin">Luke. 13.25 26 27.</note> yet in this 21. verſe he aſcendeth from that particular to a general deſcription of all falſe &amp; fayned profeſſors of the trueth, of what calling and function ſoeuer they be of in the Church or common wealth, as appeareth moſt plainly both by the ſimilitudes generally vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 17.18. &amp; 19. verſes going before: and alſo by theſe words, <hi>Not euerie one that ſaith vnto me, Lord, Lord, ſhal enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Neuertheleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal meaning and drift of Chriſt is, to terrifie the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and preachers of the word with this feareful threatning of the ſecond death: as the wordes of the 22. verſe doe neceſſarilie proue &amp; confirme. <hi>Many vvill ſay vnto me, Lord, Lord, haue vve not by thy Name pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied &amp;c.</hi> which none could truly alledge for themſelues, but ſuch onely as had bene preachers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word &amp; workers of miracles. A gift in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time almoſt peculiar to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles &amp; miniſters of Chriſt, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the certeinty &amp; truth of their doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The order or diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iii. verſes.</note>This dreadful declaration of the iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of al hypocrites &amp; fained profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb facs="tcp:18418:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the true Goſpell, conteineth two general &amp; principal parts. The firſt is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of all ſuch as profeſſe the trueth into two ſortes, fully and plainely expreſſed in the 21. verſe. the ſecond is a meeting with an obiection conteining both a kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whereby the preachers of the worde, and workers of miracles, by reaſon of their great knowledge and rare giftes, myght ſeeme as to cleere and defend them ſelues: ſo to auoide and eſcape the iuſt ſentence of eternall curſe and malediction, ſet downe in the 22. verſe, <hi>Many ſhall ſay vnto me in that day, Lord, Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And alſo a moſt wiſe and perfect, though very fearefull, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of Chriſt there unto in the 23. verſe. <hi>And then will I confeſſe to them &amp;c.</hi> wherein notwithſtanding theſe glorious works alledged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former verſe for their defence, he ſheweth that becauſe he neuer acknowledged them by reaſon of their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procriſie, and becauſe in doing ſuch works they brought forth iniquitie: therefore he muſt neceſſarily forbid them his preſence, wherein onely is all ioye and felicitye, as contrarily to be ſecluded from his preſence is all ſorowe and extreme miſerie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:5"/>
            <p>Thus we ſee both the ſumme and true meaning, and alſo the plaine and naturall diſpoſition of this part of Chriſtes ſermon conteined in theſe three verſes. Whereof I purpoſe to ſpeake particularly, not in the excellencie of wordes, or in the inticing ſpeach of mans wiſedome, but in plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and demonſtration of the trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">There are two ſortes of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of true religion.</note>
               <hi>Not euery one &amp;c.</hi> Here our Sauiour Chriſt diuideth al the worſhippers of God, and the profeſſors of his Goſpell into two ſortes: for the firſt ſentence of this verſe is equiualent, or al one in ſenſe with this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſaying, Some men ſaying vnto Chriſt, Lord, Lorde, ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen. wherein as he noteth the firſt ſort of profeſſors: ſo he deſcribeth them by their external confeſſing of Chriſt to be their Lorde and Maſter, and alſo by their end.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort he noteth in the latter, and alſo deſcribeth them by their fruites &amp; end, in theſe wordes, <hi>But he that doeth my Fathers will which is in heauen, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen:</hi> which ende although it be not expreſſed, yet it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to be ſupplied out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former part.
<pb facs="tcp:18418:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true meaning of theſe words is this. Of the external profeſſors of Chriſt, ſome doe onely profeſſe in outward ſhew: and ſome others doe both outwardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and alſo doe the Fathers wil which is in heauen: ſo that the author of this diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is our Sauiour himſelfe, and therefore it is in no wiſe to be doubted of. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the common and vſuall conuerſation of Chriſtians is ſo corrupt, that it euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declareth them to be contented and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with an outward ſeruing of God, void of inwarde ſynceritie and true beliefe: it ſhalbe requiſite and needfull, in few words to ſhew out of the word, the certaine trueth of theſe two ſortes of men. In the firſt age of the worlde, when there were but foure perſons which ſerued the true God, the Creator of heauen and earth, the holye Ghoſt teacheth, that Habel and Cain, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they both did externally profeſſe their religion, by offering of the firſt fruites of ſheepe, and of the grounde: yet Cain his profeſſion was onely in outwarde ſhewe, becauſe his outwarde ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.5.</note> being voyde of fayth, was not regarded of God. But Habels profeſſion was both in outwarde
<pb facs="tcp:18418:6"/> ſhewe, and alſo in doyng the will of God. for the ſpirit of God commending him, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth that by faith he offered a ſacrifice of greater price then Cain,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> and by that faith obteined witneſſe of God that he was righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:<note place="margin">Gen. 4.4.</note> for which cauſe it is ſaid, The Lord had reſpect to him and to his offering. In the families of Abraham and Iſaac, being then onely the viſible Church, Iſmael, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, Iaakob and Eſau, receiued Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion the externall ſigne of their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: by reaſon whereof euery of them were accompted true worſhippers of the God of Abraham: yet Iſaac and Iaakob onely were doers of the will of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.20 21. &amp; 12.16.17.</note> as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God teſtifieth in the eleueth &amp; 12. to the Hebrewes.</p>
            <p>In the 50 pſalme the Lord him ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulateth, and with great authoritie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth with the firſt ſort of profeſſors, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.16</note> 
               <hi>What haſt thou to do to declare mine ordinances, that thou ſhouldeſt take my couenant in thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">17</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing thou hateſt to be reformed, and haſt caſt my wordes behinde thee?</hi> But vnto the other ſort he ſpeaketh thus in the ſame pſalme,<note place="margin">23</note> 
               <hi>He that offreth praiſe, ſhall glorifie me, and to him
<pb facs="tcp:18418:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that diſpoſeth his vvay aright, I vvill ſhevv the ſaluation of God.</hi> wherin he forbiddeth and condemneth the outward profeſſion of his worde and ordinances, beyng ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the right diſpoſition of the heart and life: but being ioyned together, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth thereunto eternal ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A place therfore moſt fit to warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; confirme theſe two ſortes of profeſſors of Gods worde.</p>
            <p>The Prophet Eſay doeth not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe theſe ſortes of profeſſors in playne wordes: but alſo threatneth againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſort, a wonderfull iudgement of God, ſaying,<note place="margin">Eſa. 29.13.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe this people come neere me with their mouth, and honour me with their lippes, but haue remoued their heart from me, and their feare towardes me was taught by the precept of men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">14</note> 
               <hi>therefore beholde, I will againe doe a marueilous worke in this people, euen a marueilous worke, and a wonder: for the vviſedome of their wiſe men ſhall periſhe, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of theyr prudent men ſhall be hid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">15</note> 
               <hi>Woe vnto them that ſeeke deepe to hide their counſell from the Lord: for their workes are in darkeneſſe, and they ſay, Who ſeeth vs? and vvho knovveth vs?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18418:7"/> In which wordes it appeareth, both that there be in the viſible Church of God, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well hypocriticall ſeruers of God, whoſe wicked woorkes, though in reſpect of God they bee done in the light, yet in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of men they are in darkeneſſe: as alſo true and ſyncere worſhippers, which with mouth, lippes and heart, doe honour and feare the Lorde according to his precepts. It were to long, and in deede needeleſſe in ſo plaine a matter, to cite and alledge the witneſſes of all the Prophets, who as they had great experience of both theſe kindes of men, in all eſtates and degrees of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: as of Princes, Prieſtes and people: ſo they did with great aucthoritie and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe diſcouer their ſeuerall and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſinnes, and threaten againſt them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deſtruction, and the fearefull Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: as may appeare to euery one that ſhal reade with diligence &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their prophecies. Wherefore, briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conclude this point of doctrine, the three parables of our Sauiour Chriſt in the hiſtorie of the Goſpell, of the fielde, floore, and nette, written for a plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration hereof, ſhall fully ſatiſfie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:18418:7"/> euery one, that beleeueth him to be the onely teacher of all trueth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Field.</hi> Matth. 13.24, 25. &amp;c.</note> For euen as in the fielde there groweth vp not onely ſounde corne, but alſo tares, cockell, and darnell: in the floore there is not onely pure wheat,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Floore.</hi> Mat. 3.12. Luke. 3.17.</note> but alſo chaffe: in the nette not onely good things, but bad, as filth and ſuch like:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nette.</hi> Mat. 13.47</note> ſo in the militant and viſible Church, the fielde, floore and net of the Lorde, there are not onely ſyncere and faithfull, but alſo hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical and faithleſſe worſhippers of God, not onely vpright and conſtant doers of the worde, but alſo vaine and Idle talkers of the ſame: finally not only ſuch as with good conſciences, pure heartes, and fayth vnfayned doe ſerue the LORD and his Church, but ſuch alſo as be reprobate to euery good worke, whoſe ende is to be caſt eternally from the preſence of God, and to be burned as chaffe in the fearefull fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of Gods wrath and euerlaſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation. Seeyng therefore that the example of Habel and Cain in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Worlde, of Iſmael and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, Iaakob and Eſau, in the families of Abraham, and of Iſaac, ſeeyng God him
<pb facs="tcp:18418:8"/> ſelfe in the 50 Pſalme, and in the nyne and twentieth of Eſay, ſeeing alſo all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in their prophecies, and our Sauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt the doctor of all trueth, both in the three former parables, as alſo in this preſent place doeth declare, teache, and confirme the trueth of theſe two ſortes of profeſſours: who is ſo blinde that he can not ſee this? who ſo faythleſſe that will not beleeue it? who ſo impudent that will not confeſſe it? Finally, who can be ſo iniurious to his owne ſaluation, that hauing ſo manye witneſſes, and ſuch day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and continuall experience of this trueth, will not giue his goods, body, life, and all, that he may be accompted of the LORD in the dreadfull daye of Iudgement, a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and worker of his will? The vſe of this certayne doctrine ſerueth to moue all true Chriſtians, to take greater paynes and care to frame their heartes and works according to the will of GOD, then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue an outwarde ſhewe and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of godlineſſe: as alſo to feare and terrifie the heartes of all true profeſſours, from forſaking the true Churche of
<pb facs="tcp:18418:8"/> God for the impietie and vngodlines of ſome: knowing that for the triall of Gods electe, hereſies &amp; vices muſt continue in the Church, till Chriſt at his comming aboliſh them with the breath of his mouth, and cruſh all the wicked in pieces with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yron rodde and ſcepter of his kingdome: And ſo deliuer the whole gouernement of all things into the hand of God his father, that he may be al in all, to the praiſe of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glorie, and the euerlaſting comfort of all his adopted children. Nowe that we may the better ſee and know, of which ſort of profeſſors euery one of vs is: let vs heare and learne how our Sauiour Chriſt doth deſcribe the former ſort, and what is the end of this profeſſion.</p>
            <p>He ſayth, <hi>Not euery one that ſaieth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter &amp;c.</hi> in which wordes he teacheth,<note place="margin">Who be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what is their end.</note> that all the religion of this kind of worſhippers and callers vpon God, conſiſteth onely in the outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of himſelfe, and of God his Father: for here to call Chriſte, Lord, Lord, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but in word, and outward ſhewe to profeſſe Chriſt the ſonne of God to be their Lord and maſter, God himſelfe to be
<pb facs="tcp:18418:9"/> their Father, the holie Ghoſt proceeding from them both to be their ſanctifier, and themſelues to be the ſeruantes of theſe three diuers and heauenly perſons. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this firſt ſort are ſuch profeſſors, as haue onely a ſhewe of true religion and godlines, being voide of all faithfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God. The which kind of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though it ſeeme good and glorious in the ſight of men: yet the Lorde which onely looketh into the heartes of all, by his Miniſter and Prophet Ieremie calleth it the wordes of lyes,<note place="margin">Ierem. 7.3.</note> ſaying, <hi>Thus ſayeth the Lorde of Hoſtes the God of Iſrael, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende your wayes, and your workes, and I will let you dvvell in this place.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4</note> 
               <hi>Truſt not in lying vvordes, ſaying, The Temple of the Lorde, the Temple of the Lorde: this is the Temple of the Lord.</hi> Wherein the Lorde, as wee ſee, oppoſeth the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their wayes and workes, to the outwarde profeſſion of his ſeruice done in the Temple: which, being ſeparated from the other, he eſteemeth no better then the wordes of lyes. And in deede it is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for whereas this outwarde profeſſion ſheweth, and after a ſort ſpeaketh vnto
<pb facs="tcp:18418:9"/> others, that we are the true ſeruantes of God, when as we haue but a bare and idoll reſemblance of them, it maketh and ſpeaketh a manifeſt and loude lye: and therefore is iuſtly called of GOD the wordes of lyes. The bleſſed Apoſtle Paul, in the ſeconde Chapter to the Romanes, ſpeaketh moſt plainely againſt this kinde of profeſſion. His wordes be theſe:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.28.</note> 
               <hi>He is not a Ievve vvhich is one outvvarde, neither is that Circumciſion vvhich is outvvarde in the fleſhe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">29</note> 
               <hi>but he is a Ievve vvhich is one vvithin, and the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is of the hearte, in the ſpirite, not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God.</hi> In which wordes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and properties of theſe woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers euidently aypeare: for the Apoſtle affirmeth ſuch kinde of woorſhip to bee onely outwarde, ſeparated from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Circumciſion of the heart, and the ſinceritie of the worke. Likewiſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Iames condemneth the knowledge &amp; outward profeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth,<note place="margin">Iam. 2 17.24.26.</note> in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed Iewes to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he writ, becauſe they could not iuſtifie the ſinceritie therof, both by Faith, and by their works, as euery true
<pb facs="tcp:18418:10"/> Chriſtian ought and can doe, calling verie aptlie and fitlie this kind of profeſſion void of workes, a dead fayth.</p>
            <p>Iohn alſo in his firſt Epiſtle 2. Chap. calleth theſe ſeruers of God liers, in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2 4</note> 
               <hi>He that ſaieth, I knowe him, and keepeth not his commaundements, is a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the trueth is not in him.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, as it is in the Goſpel of Luke, doth moſt plainely and briefely ſet foorth vnto vs the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and qualities of theſe men: which may be a moſt fitte interpretation of this place. For with great aucthoritie and power he aſketh a reaſon, why any can be moued to ſeparate the outward worſhip, from the ſpiritual ſeruice of the heart, and ſinceritie in the worke,<note place="margin">Luke. 6.46</note> ſaying, <hi>Why call ye me, Maſter, Maſter, and doe not the thinges that I ſpeake?</hi> Wherein as he ſheweth that nothing in all the worlde, ought to mooue vs to profeſſe our ſelues to be his ſeruants, except we doe and fulfill the things which he commaundeth: ſo he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth euery kinde of profeſſion which is voide of this faithfull obedience. Thus we ſee what the firſt ſort of woorſhippers
<pb facs="tcp:18418:10"/> be: euen ſuch as in worde confeſſe, and by hearing the Goſpell preached, receiuing the Sacraments, and calling vpon God, profeſſe themſelues to be his ſeruants: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they ſecurely pretermit the dooing of Gods will, and therefore ſhall iuſtly be ſecluded from the kingdome of heauen. For theſe men, though they crie in the Church neuer ſo loude, Lorde, Lorde, they ſhall neuer be heard: though they in worde moſt gloriouſly doe confeſſe Chriſt to bee their Sauiour, yet in the daye of iudgement he will not confeſſe them: though they ſay they knowe him in this life, yet then he will profeſſe that he neuer knewe them: though they ſeeme vnto men moſt diligent woorkers of righteouſnes and pietie, yet he then iudging, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the outward appearance, but the ſincere puritie of the heart, will ſaye vnto them, Depart from me ye workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: Finally, though they ſeeme to liue and to be the children of light, yet they are dead and are the ſonnes of darknes, and therefore ſhall not, as it is affirmed here in this place,<note place="margin">The end of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers.</note> enter into the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which is the ſecond thing whereby
<pb facs="tcp:18418:11"/> they are deſcribed. Beholde therefore, all ye hypocriticall callers vpon the Name of God, your ende, your porcion, and the lot of your inheritance, which you haue, by the hardnes of your hollowe hearts which can not repent, treaſured vp vnto your ſelues againſt the day of wrath, and of the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God, who will rewarde euery man according to his workes. For you ſhall not onely be caſt out of the kingdome of heauen, from the glorious preſence of the king of all glorie: but you ſhall drinke, as a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for your iniquitie, the bitter cuppe of Gods eternall wrath and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the kingdome of darknes, and in the fearefull preſence of Satan and all the curſed enemies of Gods grace. Repent therefore, and turne vnto the Lorde, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe the foreſkinnes of your heartes, and bring foorth fruites woorthie amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life: and thinke not that becauſe you are, by the iudgement of men, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, or becauſe you are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the worde and Sacraments of Chriſt, and of Chriſtian prayers &amp; thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, you ſhall therefore in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:18418:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> iudgement of all fleſhe, ſtand in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the righteous: for euen nowe alſo is the axe put to the roote of the tree, ſo that euery tree which bringeth not forth good fruite, ſhalbe hewen downe and caſt into the fire. For there is no reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with God: but as many as haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and tranſgreſſed the lawe of nature, which was by the finger of God written in two Tables, &amp; committed to Moſes, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be iudged by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. But that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this firſt ſort of profeſſors, &amp; of their miſerable end, may be more effectuall, and profitable to worke in vs, a perfect hatred of their corrupt life, &amp; a godly feare of their dreadful death: I will briefely ſet downe ſome particular notes whereby they may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better knowen, and al other may more truely examin their own hearts, &amp; ſo clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, whether they be of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nomber or no.</p>
            <p>Firſt he that ſaieth onely vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Notes to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the falſe &amp; true woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5</note> Lord, Lord, &amp; doth not the will of God, he hath in his heart (if he doe iudge himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles precept) a far greater care and deſire to be accompted a good chriſtian amongſt men, then in deede and trueth to be ſo in the ſight of God.
<pb facs="tcp:18418:12"/> Therefore our Sauiour Chriſt forbiddeth vs, as in giuing of almes and praying: ſo in all other workes to be like vnto theſe hypocrites,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.1.2.3.4 5.</note> whome he affirmeth to haue this great loue and deſire, to appeare righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in the ſight of men. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondarily, this hypocriticall caller vpon God, doeth more buſie his head about the outward and generall worke commaunded, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſpirituall maner of doing: which he ſeldome or neuer ſincerely obſerueth. For ſo Chriſt teacheth, and alſo denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a fearefull woe againſt them, ſaying, <hi>Woe be to you Scribes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23.27.</note> 
               <hi>and Phariſes, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, for ye are like to whited tombes which appeare beautifull outward, but are within full of dead mens bones, and of all filthines:</hi>
               <note place="margin">28.</note> 
               <hi>ſo are ye alſo, for outward ye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare righteous vnto men, but within ye are full of hypocriſie and iniquitie.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the hypocrite worketh his ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecurely, coldely, and careleſſely, not in feare and trembling,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the Spirit of trueth commaundeth in the Epiſtle to the Philippians, the ſecond Chapter, and the twelfth verſe. For he ſtriueth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne corruption, to ſuppreſſe all
<pb facs="tcp:18418:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> rebellious affections &amp; luſtes, which ſtriue againſt the lawe of God, neyther to obtaine thoſe graces and giftes of regeneration, which he ſeeth wanting in himſelf, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth, with bleſſed Paule, that which is behinde, nor yet indeuoureth him ſelfe to that which is before,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.13.14.</note> folowing hard toward the marke for the price of the hye calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus: and therefore mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly bewrayeth his ſecure &amp; careleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Againe, the hypocrite hath no full ſetled and reſolued purpoſe, in life &amp; death to profeſſe and obey the trueth and will of God: but is mutable, wauering, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in all his wayes. In conſideration whereof, Barnabas, comming into Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, &amp; ſeeing the grace of God moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully multyplied vpon many,<note place="margin">Acts 11.23</note> earneſtly exhorted al, that with purpoſe of heart they would cleaue vnto the Lord. A true note to diſcerne betweene him that feareth God, and him that doeth not. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Agayne the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites care &amp; ſtudie is, to ſtay the outward and groſſer ſinnes of life, flowing from the filthy fountayne of his natural corruption: &amp; is altogether careleſſe to ſtoppe the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it ſelfe. Wherein as he bewrayeth
<pb facs="tcp:18418:13"/> great want of heauenly wiſdome, &amp; great abundance of carnall folly: ſo he can neuer ſay with inward and ſenſible feeling of the lawe of the members, and of the Spirit, as the Apoſtle Paule ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O vvretched man that I am, vvho ſhall deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of this death?</hi>
               <note place="margin">25.</note> 
               <hi>I thank God through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. Then I my ſelfe in my mind ſerue the lavv of God, but in my fleſh the law of ſinne.</hi> A peculiar worke of Gods Spirit in all his elect: which none of the children of this world euer taſted of to their comfort, neyther can do. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Agayne the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite is ſtirred vp to work wel in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men, by ſome worldly reaſon plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his owne fantaſie and fleſhly appetite, not conſtrayned, as Gods children are, with the mercy of God, and loue of Chriſt: as it is in the 130. Pſalme in theſe words: <hi>But mercie is vvith thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.4.</note> 
               <hi>that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi> And alſo in the 2. Epiſtle to the Corinth. the 5. chap. the 14. verſe.<note place="margin">2. Co. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>For the loue of Chriſt conſtrayneth vs, becauſe vve thus iudge, that if one be dead for all, then vvere all deade.</hi>
               <note place="margin">15.</note> 
               <hi>And he dyed for all, that they vvhich liue, ſhould not he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth liue vnto themſelues, but vnto him which died
<pb facs="tcp:18418:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> for them &amp; roſe againe.</hi> Wherefore as the doer of Gods wil doth abſtayne from euil, becauſe it is contrary vnto the wil of God, and doeth good, becauſe he is conſtrayned with the loue of him, which is onely good: ſo the hypocrite contrarily abſtaineth from euyll, for feare of puniſhment, and doth the thing which ſeemeth good, not conſtrained with the loue of God, but mooued of his owne will by deſire of prayſe, or hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Finally, the hypocrite in all his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, wordes, &amp; workes, doeth (although he ſometimes playnly perceyue it not) more and oftener regarde the feare, fauour, and prayſe of men, and his owne priuat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, and pleaſure, then the feare, fauour, &amp; praiſe of God, &amp; commoditie of his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Seeyng therfore that the life of theſe men conſiſteth in a ſhewe of godlines, not in the power therof, in the outward works, not in an acceptable maner of doyng, in careleſſe ſecuritie, not in a reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feare to diſpleaſe God, in a wauering mind, not in a reſolued purpoſe to perſeuer vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaying of the riuers of ſinne, neglecting the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; to conclude, in ſeeking themſelues, rather then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of God, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of
<pb facs="tcp:18418:14"/> their brethren: Let vs not onely deteſt and abhorre it, with all our heartes and ſoules, but alſo examine euery one his own eſtate and condition, that we may ſee whether we do truely ſtande in the grace of God or no. For aſſuredly, if the outwarde workes of our Chriſtian calling be done in this ſorte and maner, they neyther are, nor can be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the pledges and ſeales of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but rather the ſubtile ſleyghts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and the deceites of ſinne, whereby theſe two myghtie enemies of our redemption bewitche vs, and depriue our heartes of the ſure hope of our promiſed inheritance and ſaluation. Let him therefore that ſtandeth, both take heede leaſt he fall, and labour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to become not only a continuall eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of theſe euills, but a newe creature, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the image of Chriſt. But alas I feare me, if all Engliſh Proteſtants woulde confeſſe freely to Gods glory, and their owne ſhame, the whole corruption of al their thoughts in this behalfe, we ſhould ſee ſuch a huge maſſe and lumpe of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, as no man is able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue in heart, muche leſſe vtter in worde. For then no doubt a great nomber would ſay, All my
<pb facs="tcp:18418:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> religion is mere diſſimulation, all my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious profeſſion of the Goſpell is nothing, but a vayne ſhewe of Chriſtianitie, yea my whole life, tryed and wayed in the balance of Gods law, is lighter then vanitie it ſelf. And I woulde to God that wee were all come to this humble and godly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, as of all other our ſinnes, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of this ſecure and careleſſe hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: wherein almoſt all profeſſours are ſo drowned, that except the moſt mercyfull God by his mighty and ſtrong hande, doe rayſe them vp by faith and repentance, they ſhall periſh euerlaſtingly without any hope of redemption. Nowe therefore, deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for the loue of God, let vs not put our truſt and confidence in theſe and ſuch lyke lying words, as to ſay, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lorde, and to call Chriſt, Lord, Lord, Maſter, Maſter, or to ſay, I am baptized, I knowe the trueth, I profeſſe the Goſpell, and ſuch like: becauſe except we can iuſtifie this outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our faith to be ſyncere, and pure by the integritie of our workes, our ſauiour Chriſt telleth vs heere, that we ſhall neuer enter into the kingdome of heauen. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:18418:15"/> much for the former ſort of profeſſors, their maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, &amp; their final deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contained in theſe wordes: <hi>Not euery one that ſayeth vnto me, Lorde, Lorde, ſhal enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe followeth the ſeconde ſorte, in theſe wordes, <hi>But he that doeth the vvyll of my heauenly Father vvhich is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who be true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Chriſtian religion.</note> Wherein Chriſt deſcribeth the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heires of his Fathers kingdome, by their fruites, all which fruites be compriſed in this one ſentence, <hi>Which do my Fathers vvill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods will is done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two ſortes.</note> Wherfore we muſt learne and know, that the doyng of the Fathers wyll is of two ſortes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt ſyncere and alſo perfect, which kinde of doyng is to be founde and ſeene onely in the natural Sonne of God, Chriſt Ieſus: for his Father gyueth this teſtimonie of him,<note place="margin">Mark. 1.11</note> that in him he is well pleaſed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, ſyncere onely, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Nowe as the former is peculiar to the naturall Sonne, ſo this latter is onely proper to the adopted ſonnes of God. Who therefore are moſt fitly and wiſely by it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in this place of our Sauiour: for he meaneth not here the perfect doyng of the Fathers will (for then no fleſhe ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:18418:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> be iuſtified in the ſight of God) but the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; faithful obſeruation of thoſe things, which are agreeable vnto the will of God: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſeruers wherof ſhall enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. which words, though they be not plainly expreſſed, yet they are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to be ſupplyed, as is before declared.</p>
            <p>Nowe conſidering that the doyng of the Fathers will declareth who ſhall be ſaued, let vs heare what the doing of the Fathers will is.<note place="margin">Two things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to the doyng of Gods will.</note> The knowledge hereof ariſeth of two things, which are neceſſarily required to the acceptable working of the ſame: that is to ſay, the workes of the lawe or actions the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; the maner of doyng. the whole want of either of which is a manifeſt token eyther of infidelitie, or hypocriſie. For the firſt, that works are neceſſarily required to the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment of the Fathers will, the ſcriptures in many, yea almoſt infinite pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do teach: a few whereof, to auoyd tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes in ſo plaine a matter, I haue choſen for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of this doctrine. In the 5. of Deut. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meeke &amp; faithful ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, Moſes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth all Iſrael, not onely to learne &amp; know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; lawes of god: but alſo carefully to obſerue them, ſaying,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Heare O Iſrael the ordinances and the lawes which I propounde to you this day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deute. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>that ye may learne them, and take heede to obſerue them.</hi> Againe in the 10. of Deuter. hee hath written to the ſame effect theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Deu. 10.12</note> 
               <hi>And nowe, O Iſrael, vvhat doeth the Lorde thy God require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his wayes, &amp; to loue him, and to ſerue the Lord thy God, with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein by the way is to be noted, that the Lord God requireth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the workes themſelues conſiſting in his wayes, feare, loue, and ſeruice: but alſo the right maner of doyng, in theſe words, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule. Ioſua, as he ſucceeded Moſes in the gouernment of Iſrael: ſo alſo did he in the acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging &amp; publiſhing vnto them this doctrine, as appeareth in the 22. chap. of his booke, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ioſhu. 22.5</note> 
               <hi>But take diligent heede, to doe the commandement and lawe, vvhich Moſes the ſeruant of the Lord commanded you: that is, that ye loue the Lord your God, &amp; vvalke in all his waies, &amp; keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, &amp; cleaue vnto him, &amp; ſerue him vvith all your heart, &amp; vvith all your ſoule.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18418:16"/> Wherein the ſame doctrine concerning both the worke, and the maner of doing, almoſt in the ſame wordes is plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Iohn Baptiſt, the forerunner of Chriſt preached the ſame, ſaying,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Bring foorth therefore fruits vvorthy the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</hi> Iames the Apoſtle of Chriſt vtterly condemneth all profeſſion of faith, as vaine &amp; vnprofitable, if it want workes, when as he ſaieth, <hi>What auaileth it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.</note> 
               <hi>my brethren, though a man ſay he hath faith, vvhen he hath no vvorkes? can the fayth ſaue him?</hi> as if he ſhoulde ſay in plaine words, Faith outwardly profeſſed, without good works, can be no pledge or teſtimony at all of our ſaluation. Peter in his 1. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth, that becauſe Chriſt hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs in the fleſh, therefore we ſhoulde ſuffer after a ſort in our fleſh, by dying vnto ſinne, and liuing to God, ſo long as we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the fleſh. For he ſaieth, ſpeaking of the regenerate,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>that he henceforvvarde ſhould liue (aſmuch time as remaineth in the fleſh) not after the luſtes of men, but after the vvill of God.</hi> Iohn alſo in his firſt Epiſtle, denieth vs to haue any felowſhip with God, or any benefite of the blood of
<pb facs="tcp:18418:17"/> Chriſt, if we walke in darknes, and not in the light of trueth and godlines. For he ſaieth,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.6</note> 
               <hi>If we ſaye that we haue felowſhip with him, and walke in darknes, we lye, and doe not truely:</hi>
               <note place="margin">7</note> 
               <hi>But if we walke in the light as he is in the light, we haue mutuall felowſhip with him, and the blood of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne.</hi> Paul in the ſixe &amp; twentieth of the Actes profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth before king Agrippa, that he taught this doctrine touching the neceſſitie of workes, both to Iewe, and Gentile, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Acts. 26.19 20.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore, king Agrippa, I was not diſobedient vnto the heauenly viſion, but ſhewed firſt to them of Damaſcus, and at Ieruſalem, and throughout all the coaſtes of Iudea, and then to the Gentiles, that they ſhould repent, and turne to God, and doe workes woorthie amendment of life.</hi> Moreouer, the Spirit of God witneſſeth in the twelfth to the Hebrues, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes no man ſhall ſee GOD, ſaying,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>Followe peace vvith all men, and holines, vvithout the vvhich no man ſhall ſee the Lorde:</hi> an eſpeciall place to prooue the neceſſitie of workes. Laſtly our Sauiour Chriſt in the fiue and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth
<pb facs="tcp:18418:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Matthew, teaching that in the day of iudgement all fleſh ſhalbe tried, and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged according to the workes of loue and mercie, done in this life towardes him in his members, confirmeth and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth in his owne perſon, and worde, the infallible trueth of this doctrine: in whom, as in all other pointes of religion, ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in this, we ought fully and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to reſt. For there it is briefely concluded,<note place="margin">Matth. 25. from the verſe 34. to 46.</note> that they which gaue vnto his members meate, drincke, lodging, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and viſited the ſicke and impriſoned, ſhalbe pronounced righteous and goe into life eternall. But the vnmercifull, being voyde of theſe workes, ſhalbe pronounced curſed, and goe into euerlaſting fire, and paine.</p>
            <p>Seeing then we haue ſo many heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly witneſſes of this trueth, and that all the Prophetes in their prophecies, doe moſt earneſtly and zealouſly call the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of GOD to the obedience of his lawe, and moſt pitifully complaine of the want thereof, threatning both tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall puniſhments againſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient malefactors: we may ſafely
<pb facs="tcp:18418:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> conclude and determine, that the workes of the firſt and ſecond table, are neceſſarilie required to the doing of the Fathers will. Nowe then if it be truely preached, that without workes there is neither doing of the will of God, neither entrance into the kingdome of heauen, O Lord, what ſhall we thinke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> licentious life of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proteſtantes, or what ſhall become of this barren, and fruitleſſe profeſſion of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt? for a man may trauaile almoſt from the one ende of the land to the other, before he can finde one man like vnto iuſt Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.1.</note> that feared God and eſchewed euill, or one woman like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dorcas,<note place="margin">Acts. 9.36.</note> full of good works and almes. As therefore our ſauiour Chriſt, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the Apoſtles had moſt iuſt cauſe to complaine in their times of the want of workes, and to be grieued with the ſinnes of the people: ſo we in this laſt age haue no leſſe cauſe to complaine, neither leſſe occaſion of ſorowe. For to come vnto par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, what eſtate, calling, or degree is there, which doth not content it ſelfe onely with ſaying, Lorde, Lorde, being notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo barren in the bringing foorth
<pb facs="tcp:18418:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> of good workes? And firſt concerning the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, and vs that be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and preachers of the worde, whome this place principally doth concerne: where are the lippes of thoſe miniſters which doe preſerue knowledge, or thoſe meſſengers of God, at whoſe mouthes his poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhoulde ſeeke his lawe? Naye rather, where be not whole ſwarmes of idle, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and vngodly Curates and Readers, who neither can, nor will, goe before the deare flocke of Chriſt in ſoundnes of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and integritie of life? The cauſe of which enormitie reſting principally in the perſons them ſelues, and then in thoſe which ſent them, and nowe ſuffer them in the Church: I charge in the Lord the one, that they, ſeriouſly waying the worthines of the Lordes embaſſage, for the which they are moſt vnworthie, would volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily forgoe that calling, wherein they can not doe the Fathers will, and betake them to ſome other, which they may in a good conſcience, without offence, in ſome god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profitable meaſure diſcharge. The other I counſell and beſeeche, as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Lorde, that they would more
<pb facs="tcp:18418:19"/> diligently looke vnto their miniſterie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them, leſt not onely this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous offence, but alſo all other their ſinnes againſt God, and their brethren, be laide vnto their charge, when the heartes of all men ſhalbe made open and manifeſt before the Lorde of life. And to proceede to the learned gouernours of the Church, is there no tything of Mynt, Anyſe, and Cummin, and pretermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting waightier matters of the lawe, as Iudgement, Mercie, and Fidelitie? Doe they feede the flocke of God willingly, and carefully, as being examples vnto it, and not for filthie lucreſake, as being lords ouer Gods heritage? yf theſe things be ſo, howe can they thinke they are doers of the Fathers will? What ſhall I ſaye of our domme dogges, non reſidents, and all thoſe that ſerue mortall and ſinfull men, with ſymonie, flattering wordes, and ſeruile obedience, not lawfully to obtaine one roome in the vineyard of the Lorde, but two, three, foure, or moe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which is vnlawfull:) the which though they miſcall preferments, yet in deede they be ſo waightie charges, that
<pb facs="tcp:18418:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> the wyſeſt and ſtrongeſt of all, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſufficient for an acceptable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof. As concerning diſcipline practized in our Church by Chancelors, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries and Officials, becauſe euery one, (ſeeing all things for the moſt part begunne, continued, and ended for money in thoſe courts) doth iuſtly complaine: as I pray vnto God dayly for the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereof, ſo I doubt not but the Lorde in due and conuenient time, for the great loue he beareth towards his Church, will ſtirre vp, and arme with power, wiſdome and zeale, as well thoſe Magiſtrates, which he in mercie hath alredie giuen vs, as all thoſe alſo, with whome in time to come, he ſhall vouchſafe to bleſſe vs, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme theſe and all other the blemiſhes of his Church, according to his worde. Theſe things being thus conſidered, howe iuſt cauſe haue we to ſay with S. Paul, (whoſe time in compariſon of ours, was moſt free from corruption) <hi>All men ſeeke their ovvne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>and not that vvhich is Ieſus Chriſtes.</hi> The Lorde for his mercie ſake graunt vs true repentance. Thus much for the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:20"/>
            <p>And as for the conuerſation of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people in the lande, of what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ſo euer: I knowe not what to ſaye, or howe to ſpeake, where to beginne, or howe to make an ende. I coulde wiſhe with all my hearte, that in ſteade of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouing all the ſinnes in this lande, and Citie, my head conteyned a flood of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that I might powre out plentifull ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of teares, for all our damnable ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. For doubtleſſe the ſaying of the Prophet Oſeas is verified in this our age, by our vngodly life and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Oſeas. 4.1</note> 
               <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no trueth, nor mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, nor knovvledge of GOD in the land. By ſvvearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and vvhoring they breake out, and blood toucheth blood.</hi> Our liues doe teſtifie this to our faces: euery man doeth ſee it, and acknowledge it in his heart. We and the Catholickes (for ſo they loue to be called) doe moſt iuſtly complaine of it: we with ſorowe and griefe of heart, deſiring the ſpeedie reformation hereof: they with gladneſſe of minde, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to haue ſo good an occaſion to diſcredit the trueth of our religion. And
<pb facs="tcp:18418:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſurely to ſpeake the trueth, it is our ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe conuerſation that terrifieth both the ignorant and wauering Catholickes, and the ſimpler ſort of the common people, beyng ready to imbrace any religion (as appeareth by theſe which haue receyued, &amp; imbraced the erroneous doctrine of <hi>H. N.</hi> and his familie, falſely termed the familie of loue) from the true profeſſion of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Ieſus Chriſt. Nay, they not onely forſake vs: but they reioyce and triumphe ouer vs in the matter of workes. For the Papiſtes, they alwayes caſt in our teeth the great and famous hoſpitalitie of their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and clergie, the buylding of Abbies, Monaſteries, and Nunneries, Cathedrall churches, colledges, with many other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward works: which in deede are ſuch as do ſtoppe our mouthes, and put vs proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to ſilence. But to let them paſſe, with theſe great and coſtly workes wherein we muſt confeſſe they do exceede vs: and to come to our ſelues, and ſuch works as are required of euery one in his ſeueral calling: Where be thoſe parentes, and maſters, which doe teache in their families vnto their children and ſeruantes, the lawe and feare of God,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:21"/> walking them ſelues in the myddeſt of their houſes in vpryghtneſſe of heart? Where be thoſe gouernours that defende the fatherleſſe, and widowe, that receyue no brybe to corrupt Iuſtice, that prolong not ſentence for lucre ſake, that reſpect no perſons in iudgement, that are ready alſo without regarde of feare or fauour of men, to cut of the workers of iniquitie from the Citie of the Lorde, and to eſtablyſhe the ſeate of the faithfull? And to be ſhorte, where is that Proteſtant that feedeth the hungrie, clotheth the naked, viſiteth the pryſoner and him that is ſycke, that lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the harbourleſſe, without ceaſing or beyng wearie of well doyng? I ſpeake not this to iuſtifie the Papiſtes, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all Proteſtantes, but to ſhewe howe rare the woorkes of mercie are, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt thoſe that ſeeme to put all their ioye and felicitie in the mercies of God reuealed in Chriſt. For I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of diuers, who as they haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued grace and mercie to beleeue, and hope: ſo they are full of the fruites of loue and charitie, according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Grace receyued. The leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:18418:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> whereof I dare be bolde to preferre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the workes that euer haue bene done with an opinion to merite, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, or with deſire of prayſe of the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. As for <hi>H. N.</hi> and his family, becauſe they condemne all workes of men which are not perfect, and voyde of ſinne, which onely are to be founde in Chriſt our rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, wiſedome, and ſanctification: I leaue them to the iuſt iudgement of God, who ſhall rewarde them according to their deſerts. For it grieueth me to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider how ignorant they are of this doctrine, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the goodneſſe and neceſſitie of works. Well, howſoeuer men do pleaſe and flatter themſelues with a generall knowledge of the trueth, with a light &amp; vnſetled opinion of ſaluation, with an external ſhew of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, as ſure as the Lorde lyueth, if they can not by their workes iuſtifie this knowledge, faith, &amp; profeſſion, they ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do the Fathers will, nor enter into the kingdom of heauen. For though they be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, yet are they not of it, though they ſeeme heires of life, yet they are inheriters of death. Be not deceiued, deere brethren, for this is a true ſaying, &amp; by al means to be
<pb facs="tcp:18418:22"/> receiued: He that ſoweth to his fleſhe, ſhall of the fleſhe reape corruption: but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reape life euerlaſting. Nowe then, ſeeyng the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry floods of hypocryſie haue ouerflowen al eſtates, and degrees: are a nomber of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes any better then cloudes without water, carryed about with euery blaſt of errour and vngodlines, then corrupt trees without fruite, then ſpots and blots in the Chriſtian aſſemblies of their brethren, yea then raging waues of the ſea, foming out their owne ſhame &amp; confuſion? Therfore I beſeeche you all, in the name of Chriſt, for the mercies of God, to caſt of theſe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble clokes of religion, and vaniſhing ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of true beleefe, imbracing and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing all the woorkes of ſounde doctrine, and true godlyneſſe. I haue ſtoode the longer in this treatie, to prooue the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of woorkes, becauſe our Goſpell, which we haue receyued of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is falſely charged (as you doe ſee) to be a doctrine of libertie, and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of lyfe: as alſo for that the moſt parte of Proteſtantes are altogether ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and careleſſe, touching the obedience
<pb facs="tcp:18418:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> of faith, rather preſuming in the pryde of their hearts of the mercies of God for their ſaluation, then by humble and trembling heartes to worke, ratifie, and confirme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne conſciences the certaintie of their election.<note place="margin">Works are neceſſarie for many cauſes.</note> Therefore to ſtoppe the ſlaunderous mouth of the aduerſarie, and to terrifie the ſecure and preſumptuous profeſſor: we conclude that woorkes are neceſſarily required, not onely for doyng of the Fathers will: but alſo for the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our faith, for the confirmation of our hope, for the ſeparating of vs from all infidels and hypocrites, for the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of thoſe which are without, and within the Church, for the relieuing and ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all, eſpecially of thoſe which are of the houſhoulde of fayth, for to iuſtifie our religion to be pure and vndefiled before God the Father, for to teſtifie our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and thankefulneſſe to God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof, finally to prayſe and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the great power, Iuſtice, and mercie of God the Father, his Sonne, and the holie Ghoſt, one God, and three perſons in the whole and perfect worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:23"/>
            <p>Hitherto of the neceſſitie of woorkes: now followeth the maner of doyng, which is no leſſe neceſſarie to the fulfylling of Gods will, then workes themſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the cauſe why all our workes are acceptable to God. For albeit we doe continually cal vpon God with our lippes, and heare his worde with our outwarde eares, and bryng foorth all other apparent workes of godlines and ryghteouſnes: yet if we pray not in ſpirit, heare not with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and beleeue, and woorke by loue according to God his wyll: we do not the Fathers will, but our owne, we walke not according to the Spirit, but according to the fleſhe, and therefore muſt reape of the fleſhe corruption.<note place="margin">What is the ryght maner of doing the Fathers will.</note> But let vs ſee what this ryght maner of doyng is, whereof our ſauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh in this place, whence it is, whereof it is made, and to what end it muſt be directed: the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which cauſes wyll breede in vs a perfect knowledge of this vpryght ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working, whether it be inwarde in minde, or outwarde in maners. There is but one onely author and gyuer hereof, euen the Spirite of God, and Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> from whome proceede and come all good counſelles, pure deſires, and godly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. For although it bee left in our power (in aſmuch as the Lorde hath made vs reaſonable creatures, in ſome ſorte to reſemble his Image) to wyll this or that thing, to reaſon vpon this or that queſtion, to thinke vpon this or that matter, to ſpeake this or that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and to doe this or that woorke: yet to wyll, to reaſon, to thynke, to ſpeake, and to doe all theſe, ſo as our mercifull God requireth of his children, and ſo as they may bee acceptablie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in Chriſt, (as ſyncere obedience vnto God) it proceedeth not from fleſhe and blood, neyther from the wyll of man,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.13.</note> neyther from any other creature in heauen or in earth: but onely from the moſte comfortable Spirit of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, whoſe peculiar office is, to begynne, continue, and finiſhe in vs his holie veſſelles, this gracious maner of doyng: the which our heauenly Father, in the multitude of his mercies, hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed vs, and his Sonne our only ſauiour,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:24"/> by his death and reſurrection, hath moſt perfectly deſerued, and purchaſed for vs. So the bleſſed Apoſtle Paule teacheth, in the ſecond to the Philippians, who after he had charged them to woorke their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with feare and trembling,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> addeth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in the verſe following,<note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>For it is God that vvorketh in you both the vvill &amp; deede, euen of his good pleaſure.</hi> Which is a moſt ſtrong and forcible reaſon to ſtryke into their heartes, a reuerent feare and trembling vnder the myghtie hande of God: becauſe that although they had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to wyll, and worke: yet the chaunging of our wyll, and drawing it vnto good, the power to doe that which is vnfaynedly good, and acceptable in the ſight of God, doe proceede onely from the ſpirit of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.27.</note> Agayne the ſame Apoſtle, in the eyght to the Romanes witneſſeth, that we knowe not what to praye as we ought, but the ſpirit helpeth our infirmitie, and maketh requeſt for vs with ſyghes that cannot be expreſſed, according to the wyll of God. Wherein as he remooueth from vs this poynt of wiſedome, to knowe both what to praye, and howe, or after
<pb facs="tcp:18418:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> what maner: ſo contrarilie he aſcribeth it vnto the ſpirite of Adoption, the onely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker thereof. For it is he that moueth and ſtirreth vp in our heartes ſighes vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and not onely helpeth our infirmities, but alſo teacheth vs to pray in ſuch maner, that our worke &amp; prayer may be according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of God. So it is in al other workes which are acceptable vnto God: for thoſe only are his children, which are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of doing &amp; working the wil of God, led and guided by his ſpirit. Wherefore it is ſaid, that we haue not receyued the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to liue and worke in a ſlauiſh and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile feare: but the ſpirit of Adoption, which ſealeth and printeth in our heartes a full aſſurance of faith and hope, whereby at all times, and in all extremities we may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry, Abba, Father. So that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and plaine hereby, that all thoſe works are carnall, earthly and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueliſh, which are done after any other maner, then this: and contrarily that thoſe onely be good works, which are done after this heauenly maner, which Gods ſpirit doeth teach by the word: who therefore is called the ſpirit of trueth, and ſanctification, becauſe he onely leadeth
<pb facs="tcp:18418:25"/> vs into all trueth and holynes. Many mo places might here be alledged for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proofe of this doctrine: but becauſe the matter is plain, &amp; cannot be gainſaid with any ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of reaſon, I will omit them: onely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſing the Reader of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs &amp; the Catholicks, in the doctrine of freewill. We teach and beleeue, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we haue a natural abilitie &amp; power to wil, deſire, ſpeake, &amp; worke: yet the whole maner of vſing theſe gifts, according to the will of God, proceedeth onely from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, as we haue taught. They holde and teach the contrary: if not, let them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare plainely wherein they differ from vs, or els ioyne with vs, at the leaſt in the vnitie of this doctrine, which aſcribeth the whole glory of our new birth to God alone.</p>
            <p>Thus then we know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy maner of doing: now let vs further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whereof it ariſeth, &amp; wherin it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.18 19</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may ſtand ſtedfaſt &amp; vnmoueable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of our inheritance, both in regard of our works, &amp; alſo in reſpect of the maner of doing. It is certeine that it ariſeth of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and manifold graces of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which are proper and peculiar to his
<pb facs="tcp:18418:25"/> veſſels, neither can be at any time in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; reprobate, what pretence ſoeuer they make of religion &amp; godlines. But the time will not ſuffer me to ſpeake of all. I will briefly ſpeake of the chiefeſt &amp; moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal gifts, wherunto alſo al the other almoſt may be referred.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Fayth.</hi>
               </note> The firſt and chiefeſt of all, is true faith rooted and eſtabliſhed in our hearts: that is, a conſtant truſt in God, whereby, as he hath promiſed vnto vs in Chriſt all good thinges, &amp; is able and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to performe: ſo we are aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that he will in due and conuenient time accompliſhe his promiſe particularly vnto euery one of vs, to his glory and our ſaluation. For Peter teaching, as it is in the 15. of the Actes, how the vncleane Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles became cleane, and what was the firſt gift, whereby the holy Ghoſt purified their filthy heartes, to make them all one body with the Iewes without difference, nameth expreſly this gift of faith in theſe wordes: <hi>And GOD vvhich knovveth the hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>bare them vvitneſſe, in giuing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Ghoſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he did vnto vs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">9.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; he put no difference betweene vs and them, after that by faith he had purified their hearts.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18418:26"/> For the ſpirit of God by faith, as by a moſt fit inſtrument, doth clenſe and purge away all filthy and corrupt maner of ſeruing of God, and worketh ſanctification of life, ſo that the increaſe of faith is the increaſe of holynes. For til we be fully perſwaded that God by his holy ſpirit, and faith hath vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and incorporated vs into the body of Chriſt, to liue and be conformed according to his Image, and that wee and all our workes are accepted through him: we can neuer thinke, will, ſpeake, or doe any good thing with pure heartes. Therefore this faith, without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, ſealed in our heartes by the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God, and offering vp all our works, not in our perſonnes, but in the perſon of Chriſt, in whom they muſt needes be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably receiued, is the firſt and chiefeſt gifte of regeneration, out of the which ariſeth, though not a perfecte kinde of obedience, and ſeruice of God, (for we beleeue but in part) yet ſuch a kinde as pleaſeth God in Chriſt, profiteth his Church, and cauſeth vs to feele that peace and quietnes of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which paſſeth all wiſdome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And therefore this faith aboue all
<pb facs="tcp:18418:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> things chiefly is to be begged at the hands of our merciful father, that we may attaine vnto this right maner of doing his will: and alſo the voyce of Chriſtes Goſpell, ſounding by his miniſters in the Church, by which meanes onely ordinarily it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, is moſt diligently to be receiued and heard.</p>
            <p>The ſecond gracious gifte of the holy Spirit, though it be a fruite of the former,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Hope.</hi>
               </note> as the other which followe are: yet it hath a ſeuerall vſe. I meane a ſtedfaſt and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hope, for the full and perfect fruition of eternall life. For as faith doth apprehend, applie, and as it were by a hand reache vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery man particularly, the promiſes of God concerning eternall life in Chriſt, and alſo Chriſt himſelfe, in whom all thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are Yea and Amen fully and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſhed: ſo hope vſeth, enioyeth, and after a ſort, euen in this life poſſeſſeth, all thoſe thinges which are promiſed of God, and apprehended by faith, yea euen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life it ſelfe. In conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Apoſtle affirmeth that we are ſaued by hope, that is to ſaye, by the benefite of hope we enioye and poſſeſſe alreadie our
<pb facs="tcp:18418:27"/> ſaluation, though as yet abſent. So that he which looketh vpon preſent things that are ſeene, to haue ſaluation in them, he renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth hope, which gift only in the elect is the faithfull keeper, and poſſeſſor of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purchaſed by Chriſt. For it is called by the Spirit of God, in the 6. to the Heb. the ancre of the ſoule, in theſe wordes: <hi>Which we haue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.19.</note> (meaning hope) <hi>as an ancre of the ſoule, both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and it entreth into that vvhich is vvithin the vaile, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the forerunner is for vs entred in,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20</note> 
               <hi>euen Ieſus that is made an hye Prieſt for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of Melchiſedech.</hi> For as the whole vſe of the Ancre is, to holde faſt the ſhippe in one ſure and certaine place, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all tempeſts and waues bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt it) becauſe it entereth into the very depth and bottome of the ſea, there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king faſt hold: euen ſo the principall vſe of hope is to enter into the heauen of heauens, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God, and to hold faſt our ſoules there with him, notwithſtanding all the waues &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes of Satan, ſinne, and condemnation do beate daily &amp; continually againſt them. As therfore faith is neceſſary to leade vnto
<pb facs="tcp:18418:27"/> Chriſt: ſo hope is alſo neceſſary to keepe vs alwayes with him. In regard whereof, we are by the holy Ghoſt earneſtly exhorted, in the Chriſtian race which is ſet before vs, as to run with patience, ſo eſpecially to looke to Ieſus the author &amp; finiſher of our faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.2</note> who for the ioy that was ſet before him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the Croſſe, &amp; deſpiſed the ſhame, &amp; is ſet at the right hand of the throne of God. Whereby it appeareth, that this hope doth moſt liuely ſet before our conſciences, the preſence of God &amp; Chriſt, with the fruition of the kingdome of glorie: &amp; ſo worketh in vs an vnſpeakeable ioye and patience in all aduerſities. Whereof none of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate, or malignant church hath euer taſted to their ſaluation, nether ſhall do: but the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God do not only taſt hereof, but alſo leade the whole courſe of their life in this hope, as in the preſence of Chriſt &amp; God: for which cauſe they are ſaid to walke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God.<note place="margin">Gen. 5.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third gift is a ſincere loue of God &amp; man,<note place="margin">3 Loue.</note> a moſt certaine and infallible note of a true Chriſtian, and more profitable to our brethren &amp; the Church of God, then either of the former: as the Apoſtle teacheth in the firſt to the Corinthians 13. ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.13</note> 
               <hi>And
<pb facs="tcp:18418:28"/> nowe abideth faith, hope, loue, euen theſe three: but the chiefeſt of theſe is loue.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe faith doeth apprehende thoſe things we haue not, hope doth retaine and enioye them: but loue doth drawe out of vs the daily exerciſe and wiſe employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the talents receiued, to the benefite of the Church. So that for apprehending benefits that are abſent, faith is the chiefeſt, for the ioyfull retayning of them, hope is the chiefeſt, but for the vſe and employing of them to the edification of others, loue is the chiefeſt, and therfore in this reſpect iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truely preferred of the Apoſtle, if we attribute to euery one their proper vſes and effectes. If then we purpoſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a right maner of fulfilling the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wil, we muſt imbrace this grace alſo, and gift of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.14.</note> that al our workes maye ſauour and be done in loue. Vnder loue I comprehend zeale, a moſt excellent gift giuen vnto the Saints of God: for to this end Chriſt hath giuen himſelfe,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> that he might redeeme vs from all iniquities, and purge vs to be a peculiar people to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, zealous of good workes. So we ſee that the Lord hath giuen vs his Sonne,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:28"/> that we ſhoulde loue him which loued vs firſt, that we ſhould ſerue him diligently &amp; zealouſly all the dayes of our life: For as that ſeruice of men which is done by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, careleſſely, and negligently, is iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hated and reiected: ſo the Lorde hateth and reiecteth all ſeruice of man, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from this chearefull loue, and earneſt zeale of his glorye. Let vs then adioyne vnto the two former, this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gift of loue, which, as it expelleth care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecuritie, colde affection in the ſeruice of GOD, hatred, ſtrife, contempt in due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties due to men (whereof ariſeth a fayned &amp; corrupt maner of ſeruice:) ſo it cauſeth and encreaſeth the pure and vndefiled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing the Fathers will, wherefore it is recorded that they that dwell in loue, doe dwell in God, and God in them,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.16</note> becauſe he is loue.</p>
            <p>The fourth gift is a reuerent feare of God:<note place="margin">4 Feare.</note> a principall and a ſingular point of wiſedome, moſt fit and conuenient for his children to haue and practiſe towards their heauenly Father, in all their counſels and works. For ſuch is the pride of our nature, the dulnes of our heartes, and the lacke of
<pb facs="tcp:18418:29"/> wiſdome, that we ſhould behaue our ſelues preſumpteouſly, ſecurely, and raſhly before the preſence of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father: were it not for this reuerent feare &amp; trembling we haue receiued at his hand, for the obteining of a more pure &amp; ſyncere maner in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice &amp; worſhip. Neither muſt we thinke, as ſome haue falſely imagined, &amp; to the great hurt of the Church taught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this feare in vs proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any diffidence, or diſtruſt in the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment of Gods merciful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes towards vs: but rather from a moſt vehement ſorow, &amp; inward feeling bred in our hearts, by the earneſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauie burthen of all our ſinnes, and the deepe ſerious waying of the euerlaſting wrath of GOD, moſt iuſtly deſerued. So the bleſſed Apoſtle teacheth in the ſeconde to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.11</note> ſaying, <hi>Beholde, this thing that ye haue bene godly ſorie, what great care it hath vvrought in you, yea vvhat clearing of your ſelues, yea what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, yea vvhat feare, yea hovv great deſire, yea vvhat zeale, yea vvhat puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> In which words we ſee how the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of god maketh that godly ſorow (which the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhewed for their great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb facs="tcp:18418:29"/> of Chriſtian diſcipline in the matter of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication) to be the mother &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this reuerent feare, which we owe vnto God alone, in that he is our maſter: for he ſaith, If I be your maſter, where is my feare? Neither is this feare giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs to be any occaſion of diſtruſt, or deſpaire, for that is peculiar to the ſeruile &amp; ſlauiſh feare of thoſe, which are meere ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: But contrarily to make vs wiſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, carefull, and circumſpect in all the actions of our life, leſt we either by an euill worke, or corrupt maner of doing, iuſtly procure againſt vs, and kindle the wrath of ſo mercifull a Father. Alſo it ſtirreth vp our heartes to moſt zealous and effectuall prayers, as we ſee in the example of Chriſt himſelf,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>who in the daies of his fleſh did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp prayers &amp; ſupplications, with ſtrong crying, &amp; teares vnto him, that was able to ſaue him from death, and was alſo heard in that which he feared.</hi> What cryes, teares, prayers, &amp; ſupplications the Apoſtle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the hiſtory of Chriſt his paſſion &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings doth plainly expreſſe, ſo as it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to ſtand thereupon. Only this is to be noted, that ſeeyng this feare was in Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:18418:30"/> who was free from all ſinne, it ought not to be thought to be any ſinnefull infirmitie, but rather a ſingular meane to helpe and keepe vs within the bonds, &amp; liſtes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian obedience. Therefore we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Spirit of God, after this ſort to ſerue and pleaſe our heauenly Father: as in very many other places of the ſcripture, ſo in the 12. to the Hebr. eſpecially, in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore ſeeing wee receiue a kingdome which cannot be ſhaken, let vs haue grace, wherby we may ſo ſerue God, that we may pleaſe him with reuerence and feare.</hi> The reaſon is added, <hi>For euen our God is a conſuming fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">29</note> Likewiſe S. Peter, in the firſt Chapter of his 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, giueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame precept of feare to be obſerued in the whole courſe and race of our life,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17</note> ſaying, <hi>And if ye call him Father which without reſpect of perſons iudgeth according to euerie mans worke: paſſe the time of your dwelling here in feare.</hi> In which two places, not onely feare is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: but two moſt effectual reaſons are rendred thereof. Firſt, we muſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, tremble, and feare God, becauſe he is a conſuming fyre, ready to burne vp and
<pb facs="tcp:18418:30"/> conſume all falſe worſhippers, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall profeſſors of his feare. Seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, becauſe he will iudge euery man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regarde of perſon, according to his workes. We muſt therefore feare him, leſt our workes be found ſuch as cannot abide the fierie triall of the Spirite of truth and ſinceritie, and the righteous iudgement of the law of libertie: For certainly there ſhalbe iudgement mercileſſe to him, that in a reuerent feare of God ſheweth no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. And therefore to make an ende of this moſt neceſſarie point of doctrine, we muſt with both handes, yea with all our heartes embrace the feare of the Lorde, without the which no man can pleaſe and ſerue God aright. And the rather for that the wiſeſt amongſt men, Salomon, aſcribeth vnto thoſe that feare the Lorde bleſſednes, and to them that doe not, hardnes of heart. his woordes be theſe:<note place="margin">Prou. 28.14.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth alway: but he that hardeneth his heart ſhall fall into euil.</hi> Yf then we be deſirous to worſhip our God aright accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will, we muſt haue our heartes kept in awe by this moſt worthy and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gift of feare, that we may auoyd hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:18418:31"/> of heart, preſumption of minde, ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of conſcience, and all other negligent careleſnes, which as they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to this heauenly grace of the holy ſpirit of God, ſo they breed and cauſe a moſt corrupt and abominable maner in ſeruing of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>The fift &amp; laſt gift is a continual &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful watchfulnes againſt all the enemies of the former graces co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto vs, not only for the retaining &amp; keeping of them: but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daily growing &amp; increaſing in the ſame, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſure of the age of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſt, that at his comming we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing founde waking &amp; watching with the wiſe virgins, &amp; not ſtumbring and ſleeping with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fooliſh ones, may be ioyfully recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the bridegromes cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, to reigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him in glory for euer. For ſeing we haue ſo many, ſo mighty &amp; malicious enemies, which moſt ſubtilly go about to root out of our hearts al the foreſaid graces, &amp; to fil vs ful of all iniquitie: we are neceſſarily in all ſobriety of perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al maner of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſupplication, to watch diligently in faith, in hope, in loue, in feare, that we may ſtand faſt &amp; continue vnto the end, in doing &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhing our Fathers wil, in deſpite
<pb facs="tcp:18418:31"/> of all the aduerſaries of Gods grace, &amp; our ſaluation. This is Pauls counſel, or rather the commaundement of the holy Ghoſt, who hauing commended vnto the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians the ſhielde of faith, and the helmet of hope, as principall partes of Chriſtian ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, adioyneth thereunto this profitable commandement concerning watchfulnes, ſaying,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Watch thereunto vvith all perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance and ſupplications for all Saintes.</hi> The ſame precept of watching is in diuers other places of Paul his epiſtles, namely in the firſt to the Corinthians 16. where he ſaith, <hi>Watch, ſtand faſt in the faith, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.13.</note> And in the firſt to the Theſſal. 5. chap.<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs not ſleepe as doe other, but let vs vvatch and be ſober.</hi> wherein we may obſerue by the way, that this watchfulnes is onely in the children of light and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not in the children of darkenes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: whoſe propertie is careleſſely to ſleepe, when they ſhoulde be moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and watchefullye occupied in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging foorth the workes of Chriſtian obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Likewyſe our Sauiour Chriſt, beeyng verye well acquaynted with our infirmities, and knowing the drouſineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:18418:32"/> of our nature, ſtraightly chargeth his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and all other to watche, rendring a moſt effectuall reaſon thereof in theſe words,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.35</note> 
               <hi>Watch therefore, (for ye know not when the maſter of the houſe will come, at euen, or at midnight, at the cocke crow, or in the dawning) leſt he comming ſodeinly ſhould finde you ſleeping:</hi>
               <note place="margin">36</note> 
               <note place="margin">37</note> 
               <hi>and theſe things vvhich I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all men, Watch.</hi> Not only this generall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Chriſt: but alſo the ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of his diſciples for the lacke hereof, and the double repeticion of the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the ſame place, proueth the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this gifte in theſe wordes,<note place="margin">Ma. 26.38.</note> 
               <hi>Tarrie ye here and watch with me:</hi> after comming to them againe, and finding them a ſleepe, he ſaid vnto Peter,<note place="margin">40</note> 
               <hi>What? coulde ye not watch with me one houre? watch, and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the ſpirit in deede is ready,</hi>
               <note place="margin">41</note> 
               <hi>but the fleſhe is weake.</hi> Conſidering then the weakneſſe &amp; drowſineſſe of our nature, which appeared in the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Apoſtles in that moſt dangerous time, and the reproofe of the Apoſtles: we are not onely in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to holde the neceſſitie of this watche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:32"/> but in euery thing we take in hand to put it in bre and practiſe. For it is that gift of the holy Ghoſt, which maketh Gods children carefull, and ſtudious, not onely to do the Fathers will, (for that may be after ſome ſort in the reprobate and caſtawayes) but to doe it with that aſſurance of faith, with that ſtedfaſtneſſe of hope, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that zeale of his glorie, that loue of our brethren, that reuerent feare of his Maieſtie, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to vs in the word, and alſo which is moſt conuenient and proportionable to ſuch ſpirituall graces of knowledge, as we haue receiued: of which things carnal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors haue litle or no care at al. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although they may do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes which God hath decreed to be done, for good and neceſſary purpoſes, yet being voyde of this right maner of doing, they can neuer doe the will of the Father, ſo, as he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the whole matter,<note place="margin">The end, Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> wherein this true maner of ſeruing God conſiſteth: nowe we are to ſpeake briefly of the ende whereunto it is directed. This ende is the glorie and honour of God, which of al men, at all times, and in all actions is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb facs="tcp:18418:33"/> to themſelues, as the chiefe and principall marke of mans life. For albeit we may regarde in many things our owne ſelues, and the commoditie of our brethren: yet ſo farre forth we muſt doe this, as they are referred and applyed to the glory and honour of God, which ought to be more deare and precious vnto vs, then our owne ſaluation. For ſo it was vnto Moſes, who, rather then the Lords mercie ſhould not be magnified in pardoning the ſinnes of the people (which he was perſwaded was the onely meanes of glorifying God) ſpake in this maner vnto him,<note place="margin">Exo. 32.32.</note> ſaying, <hi>Therefore nowe if thou pardon their ſinne, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhall appeare: but if thou wilt not, I pray thee, raſe me out of the Booke which thou haſt vvritten.</hi> So likewiſe Paule, in the nynthe to the Romanes ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>I would wiſhe my ſelfe to be ſeparated from Chriſt, for my brethren that are my kinſemen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſhe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>which are the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites &amp;c.</hi> meaning, that ſuch was his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes them, that if it were the Lords will to glorifie himſelfe by their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, rather then it ſhould not come to
<pb facs="tcp:18418:33"/> paſſe: he wiſſheth himſelfe to be eternally ſeparated from Chriſt, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to receyue his portion with all the damned ſoules in the dungeon of darcke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Theſe two examples of the deare ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and beloued children of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and teach vs, not onely that we muſt ſet before our eyes in all our actions, the glorie of God, but alſo preferre the ſame before all the pleaſures of ſinne, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our owne life and ſaluation: wiſſhing rather to die, and forſake willingly all the tranſitorie pleaſures of this miſerable life, yea to be eternally condemned, then that the Lord ſhould be diſhonoured by our life and ſaluation. For as the glorie of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſurmounteth the body, the ſoule, the honour, and all that belongeth vnto man: ſo it ought to be in greater price and eſtimation with vs, and muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually be preferred aboue all thinges, and neuer be brought into the ballance of compariſon with them. The want of which zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the glorie of God in all our doings, and the preferring of earthly thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heauenly, temporall before ſpirituall, as it breedeth, and nouriſheth a corrupte
<pb facs="tcp:18418:34"/> maner of profeſſion: ſo it defileth all our counſelles and workes, and carrieth vs headlong to the loue of the world, which is contrarie to the pure, vehement, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting loue of God. Wherefore as all the former giftes and graces are neceſſarie to this right maner of ſpirituall ſeruice: ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is this end, of all things moſt neceſſarily to be reſpected of al true Chriſtians, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the examples of Moſes and Paule, that whatſoeuer we do,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.51.</note> we may do it (as we are commaunded) to the glorie of God. Theſe thinges being moſt truely taught, not by the vanitie and weakenes of mans reaſon, neither by the vncertaine and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table opinions of men, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſure word of Chriſt, the Prophets, and Apoſtles, we are in no wiſe to wauer or doubt of the trueth hereof, but to receiue them, as they be in deede, the wordes of God, with full purpoſe of heart to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. So doing we ſhall not onely knowe what it is to doe the Fathers will, but alſo haue experience thereof, in our owne ſelues: a thing of all other, as moſt rare in the world, ſo moſt chiefly to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Let vs then heare in a word or two,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:34"/> for our further inſtruction, and for the cleare vnderſtanding of this place, what it is to doe the fathers wil.<note place="margin">What it is to doe the Fathers will.</note> To doe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will, is in faith, hope, loue, and feare, with all maner of carefull watching, and perſeuerance, to worke thoſe things which be commaunded in the Lawe and worde, that GOD thereby may be glorified: for to doe the thing commaunded, and faile in the maner of doing, is an halfe and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yea rather no ſeruice of God at all: to faile in both is Atheiſme, to fayle in the worke, and yet to boaſt of the affection of the minde, and to be perſwaded to haue the right maner of doing, is carnall libertie and licentious preſumption. Contrarilie to haue and delight in both is ſound godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pure and vndefiled Religion, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God the Father.<note place="margin">Matt. 6.10.</note> And therefore our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt in the ſixte of Matthewe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto his Diſciples a right and a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fourme of praying, commandeth them, and in their perſons all the faithfull, to deſire God to giue them grace, not onely to doe the thinges commaunded, but alſo to obſerue this right maner of doing in this peticion, <hi>Thy vvill be done in earth as
<pb facs="tcp:18418:35"/> it is in heauen:</hi> meaning by doing of the Fathers will, the things he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded being agreeable to his will, and by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>In earth as it is in heauen,</hi> the right maner of doing: whereby appeareth the neceſſitie of both theſe pointes, whereof we haue ſpoken. For he ſaith not, Let that be done in earth, which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or let thoſe things be done in earth which God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed: but, Let them be done ſo, and in ſuch maner, as they be in heauen: that is to ſay, purely, readily, willingly, zealouſly, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and continually, to the glorie of God, and the comfort of his people. For the will of GOD at all tymes, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in earth, yea and in hell alſo is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes done and fully accompliſhed, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there come any thing to paſſe, but that onely which the Lorde hath decreed. In conſideration whereof our Sauiour chargeth vs in the petition, as wee haue heard, both to doe the Fathers will, which is neceſſarie, and alſo to doe it ſo, as it is done in heauen: the which onely maketh our miniſterie and ſeruice acceptable vnto him.</p>
            <p>Nowe that we ſee the trueth and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:18418:35"/> of this doctrine concerning the doing of Gods will: let vs more particularly applie it vnto our ſelues, that we maye the better knowe whether we be the doers of the worde, and not onely hearers, which can haue no hope and aſſurance of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And to let paſſe all thoſe that ſwarue from the ſounde doctrine of trueth, and godlyneſſe, as Atheiſtes and infidels, which haue neither workes, nor any grace of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, and Iewes which are voyde of true faith in the crucified Meſſias, let vs examine by the rule of this trueth, all thoſe that ſeeme to embrace Chriſte Ieſus and his true Religion, as Libertines, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, and carnall Proteſtantes. The Libertine and carnall Proteſtant are by it moſt iuſtly condemned, becauſe they haue no workes at all, neither any ſoundneſſe of faith or Religion: but onely a falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and vaine ſhadowe of both, as the Apoſtle Iames teacheth in the whole trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Epiſtle. The Catholicks, though they haue many outwarde and glorious woorkes to alledge for them ſelues, yet they faile altogether in the maner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for not onely their iudgement by falſe
<pb facs="tcp:18418:36"/> doctrine is corrupted,<note place="margin">The laſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentine Councell, the ſixt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and 14. Canon. Trid. the laſt, the 25. Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and firſt decree. Trid. the laſt, Seſſion 14. Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in that they teache that workes in parte doe iuſtifie, that they are accepted the better for the vertue and interceſſion of Sainctes departed, that the ſacrifice of Chriſte his oblation onely waſheth awaye ſinnes committed before Baptiſme: Laſtly that a temporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heere and in Purgatorie, can ſatiſfie and ſufficiently recompence that tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whereby the perfecte Lawe and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Iuſtice of God is broken: but alſo they fayle in all thoſe poyntes, which we haue taught to appertaine to the right maner of doing the Fathers will.<note place="margin">Triden. the laſt, Seſſion 6. Canon 15. and 16.</note> Touching faith, they teache and beleeue that it is a poynt of humilitie, contrary to preſumption, to wauer and doubt of our ſaluation. And therefore calling vpon God in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they ſhall neuer receiue any thing at his hand. Touching a ſtedfaſt hope, which onely looketh vnto Ieſus Chriſte the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and finiſher of our ſaluation, and that glorie which he hath purchaſed for vs in the preſence of his Father, they can neuer haue it: both becauſe their faith is wauering, from whence this hope muſt proceede, and alſo becauſe they holde and teach, that there
<pb facs="tcp:18418:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> be other places then heauen for the ſoules of men to reſt in after this life. Touching loue and charitie, which principallye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the ſaluation and profite of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: doe they not moſt vncharitably, and flatly againſt the edification of the Church of GOD, (which in all publike actions vnder paine of damnation muſt be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) teach and beleeue, that ignoraunce of Gods religion is the mother of deuotion? doe they not reade the word, pray, and giue thankes in a ſtrange language, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen tongue? doe they giue (which is not theirs to giue) abſolution from ſinnes of meere loue, and not for money? Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doe they vexe, grieue, torment, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and burne the bodyes of Gods Saintes, after two or three light confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and diſordered examinations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they loue their bodyes, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their ſoules? No verely, theſe thinges rather doe manifeſtly declare, not onely that they are deſtitute of charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men: but alſo of pure loue towards God. For he that ſayeth he loueth God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for how can he that loueth not his brother, whome
<pb facs="tcp:18418:37"/> he hath ſeene, loue GOD whome hee hath not ſeene? As for the true feare of God, howe can it be in them, ſeeyng that they holde that Gods eternall wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſinnes, eyther paſt, or to come, can iuſtly and ſufficiently be appeaſed by tryfling pardons, and bulles giuen of mortall men? and to be ſhort, conſidering that they teach that all ſinnes following baptiſme muſt be purged, not by the blood of Chriſt, but be counteruailed, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued by good workes, as they falſelye terme them, or pardons and abſolutions of ſinfull men,<note place="margin">Trident. the laſt. Seſſion 25. in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</note> or equall puniſhment here in earth or in purgatorie? the LORD forgiue them, they know not where. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for carefull watchefulneſſe to retaine all the foreſayde graces, howe can it be in them, ſeeyng they are voyde and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of theſe gracious giftes of GOD? If therefore they haue anye (as in deede they haue much) it is not, neither can bee for theſe thinges: but to maintayne and increaſe their vſurped power and auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of both the ſwordes. And therefore knowing euerye man to be by the inſtinct of nature giuen to acknowledge GOD,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:37"/> and with ſome kinde of watchefulneſſe to ſerue him, they haue out of the follye and vanitye of their owne braynes, drawne out a kinde of ſeruice, which ſtandeth onely in outwarde ceremonies, and bodily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, wherein they haue bene, and are very watchefull: as in ſaying certeyne number of maſſes, prayers, diriges, and ſuch like, in doyng of penaunce, goyng on pilgrimage, vſing of holy water and holy bread, offeringes, carnall faſtinges, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, anointinges, with infinite moe of the ſame ſorte. All which inuentions of men are directly contrary to that worſhip, which our Sauiour Chriſt witneſſeth to conſiſt in Spirit and trueth, and therefore iuſtly condemned. For if bodily exerciſes which may be well vſed, are neither profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table of them ſelues, neither anye parte of the worſhippe of God: doe we not iuſtlye abhorre and deteſt the traditions which are after the commaundements and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of men? And nowe as it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that they fayle in theſe thinges, ſo alſo in the ende, whereby all our actions muſt be meaſured and eſteemed. For in that they aſcribe righteouſneſſe in parte to
<pb facs="tcp:18418:38"/> their workes which they haue done,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.27. Eph. 2.8.9.</note> they may with as good reaſon challenge a part of the glory of their redemption: whereby the Lord of neceſſitie muſt be robbed of his honour, to whome belongeth all glory and dominion. Thus much I haue ſpoken on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſkilful, malicious, and obſtinate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, not of the poore ignorant ones, which neither haue knowen the trueth, neither haue their conſcience ſet &amp; fixed in hereſie. Albeit I dare affirme that neither theſe, neither any other obſtinate and wilfull he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, or ignorant perſon, doeth or can doe the Fathers will: Becauſe as hereſie is ſtrong to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne: ſo ignorance is blinde, and cauſeth vs to fall into the pit of conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Seeyng therefore that this doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſte condemneth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, Infidels, Iewes, Libertines, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and al other ſects of heretikes, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons, &amp; euery one that is not of the true Church of God, we had neede with all care and ſtudye to trie and examine the very bottome of our heartes, and rippe vp all the inwarde and ſecret corners of our conſciences, leaſt we alſo be iuſtly reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:18418:38"/> and condemned by the ſame. For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly we muſt all in the day of iudgement be tried, and made knowen to the worlde by the practiſe of this doctrine, to the glory of God, &amp; the comfort of our owne hearts, whether we haue truelye taſted of the gifte of God in Chriſt, or no? but if we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with the ſhadowes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde godlyneſſe, as with the outwarde vſe of Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lorde, with lippe ſeruice, and ſuch exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall kinde of profeſſion, denying the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof in our heartes, and workes: wee deceyue our owne heartes, we depriue our ſoules of the ioyfull fruition of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and walke, as faſt as can be, towards the place of darkeneſſe and endeleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For this is the doctrine of the Sonne of God, <hi>Not euerye one that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto me, Lorde, Lorde, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth the will of my heauenly Father, which is in heauen.</hi> Goe to then, you carnall and worldely Proteſtants, that ſaye, Lorde, Lorde, God be prayſed, and God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for all his giftes &amp;c. I demaunde this of you in the perſon of Chriſt, whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
<pb facs="tcp:18418:39"/> I am though moſt vnworthie, ſhewe me this your fayth, and profeſſed religion by your workes, and iuſtifie it before me &amp; the Church of God. For was not Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham our father iuſtified through woorkes, when he offered Iſaac his ſonne vpon the altar? Was not Rahab the harlot iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through woorkes, when ſhe had recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the meſſengers, and ſent them out an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way? Knowe therefore for a certein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, all you that profeſſe the feare of God, that fayth profeſſed without woorkes is dead: Yea as the bodie without breath: ſo fayth without woorkes is cleane dead, and therefore but a ſhadowe of the true fayth which woorketh by loue. But ye wyll ſay, We knowe and beleeue that Chriſt is the Sonne of God. What then? the deuils beleeue alſo, tremble, yea and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,<note place="margin">Acts. 19.15.</note> IESVS wee knowe, and Paul wee knowe, but who are yee? Yea, but wee by Baptiſme, and the Sacrament of thankeſgiuing, are become the profeſſours of Chriſt. Was not Iudas a profeſſour alſo, yea a preacher and a worker of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? But wee are no enemies and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Chriſt, as he was. No more
<pb facs="tcp:18418:39"/> were thoſe diſperſed Chriſtians to whome Iames wrytte, nay they ſuffered manye troubles for the outwarde profeſſion of the trueth: whome notwithſtanding he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth for want of workes.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges therefore are but clokes of hypocriſie, and wordes of lyes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Satan carryeth away manye from the wayes of godlineſſe and life, into the paths of wickedneſſe and deſtruction. It is not then the outwarde ſhewe of Chriſtianitye, in countenaunce, worde, and worke, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth any thing,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17</note> but onely a newe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Chriſt. In conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I heartily deſire and beſeeche you all, from the hygheſt vnto the loweſt, both to flye this damnable corruption of worldly and carnall men, and to giue all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to keepe and obſerue this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maner of doing the Fathers will. Take vnto you aboue all thinges fayth, ioyne vnto faith, hope, vnto hope, loue and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindeneſſe, vnto brotherly kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reuerent feare of the Maieſtie of GOD, vnto a reuerent feare, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cefull watchfulneſſe in all good workes. For if theſe be amongeſt
<pb facs="tcp:18418:40"/> you, and abound more and more according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſte: they will make you that ye neyther ſhall bee idle, nor vnfruitefull in the profeſſion of Chriſt and his Goſpell. But he that hath not theſe thinges, what face and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſo euer he carrieth of religion, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, learning, and vertue, he is blinde, and can not ſee farre into the myſterie of godlineſſe, or els hath through ingratitude altogether forgotten, that he was purged from his olde ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Seeyng then by this meanes, not onely an entring ſhall be miniſtred vnto you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the euerlaſting kingdome of our Lorde and Sauiour IESVS Chriſt: but alſo your effectuall calling, and eternall election ſhall be fully ratified vnto your owne heartes and conſciences, ſo as you maye knowe perfectly that nothing can ſeparate you from the loue of GOD: if there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of loue, if anye fellowſhippe of the Spirit, if anye compaſſion and mercie, thinke on thoſe thinges which you haue now heard, fulfill theſe things, and you ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:18418:40"/> neuer fall, but the God of peace ſhalbe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with you, neither ſhall the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euer depart from you. But peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome will ſay, O Lorde, who is able for theſe things? In deed in reſpect of man it is vnpoſſible, but with God as all other things, ſo this is poſſible, and hath bene by his power wrought in man. For doeth not the holy Ghoſt witnes of Dauid,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.14. 2. King. 18.3.</note> that he was a man according to Gods own heart? of Hezechia, that he did vprightly in the ſight of the Lord, according to al that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid his father had done? of Ioſia,<note place="margin">2. King. 23.25.</note> that he turned to the Lorde with all his heart, and with all his ſoule, and with all his might, according to all the lawe of Moſes? of Zacharie and Elizabeth his wife,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.6.</note> that they were iuſt before God, and walked in all the ordinances of the Lord without reproofe? of Nathanael,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.47.</note> that he was an Iſraelite in deede, in whom was no guile?<note place="margin">Mat. 8.10.</note> of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, that there was not the like fayth in Iſrael? of Anna,<note place="margin">Luke 2.37.</note> that ſhe liuing a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe foure ſcore and foure yeeres, went not out of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, but ſerued God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faſting and prayers night and day? finally of all the primitiue Church both men and
<pb facs="tcp:18418:41"/> women, immediatly after the aſcenſion of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they continued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one accord in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles doctrine,<note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> &amp; felowſhip, in breaking of bread, in prayers &amp; ſupplications, eating their meate together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gladnes &amp; ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, prayſing God, yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleued were of one heart, and of one ſoule, neither any of them ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he poſſeſſed was his owne: but they had all things common? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing we are compaſſed with ſo great a cloud of witneſſes, of kings, of Prophets, of Iewes, of Gentiles, of men, of women, which haue ſerued the Lorde in this right maner of doing: let vs alſo caſt away eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that preſſeth downe, and the ſinne that hangeth ſo faſt on: let vs runne with ioye &amp; pacience in this ſtraight race which is ſet before vs, without wearines and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For doubtles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> want of thoſe things, ioyned with the practiſe of the contrary vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are the cauſes of all the puniſhments of God, that are or haue bene in the world. For whence commeth warre, famine, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, tranſlation of Monarchies &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ouerthrowes of families, Townes, Cities, &amp; whole Countries: but from this,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:41"/> that we doe not the will of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it is done in heauen? For want whereof, we that liue nowe in this peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble land flowing with milke and hony, and in the light of the Goſpel ſhining vnto vs, for the ſpace of twentie golden yeeres, are of all other moſt inexcuſable. For who can tell &amp; repeate the warnings, whereby God in mercie hath called vs to repentance, and reformation of our liues? But who hath ſhed foorth as yet the Chriſtian teares of repentance? Not foure yeres agoe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord did as it were with his owne hand ſet a ſtarre in the heauens, whereof the wiſeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomer that liueth, can giue no reaſon. Since that, we haue bene admoniſhed by a great and ſtrange Comete in the ayre, by earthquakes, inundations of waters, all which ſignes &amp; foreru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners of Gods wrath are returned to him again, as being vnable to mollifie our ſtony hearts, that we might turne vnto the Lord. Onely his glorious Goſpel abideth with vs: but alas it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me to conſider howe litle place it fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in our hearts: how careleſly receiued, and how generally by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life &amp; conuerſation of Chriſtians, it is defamed &amp; diſcredited:
<pb facs="tcp:18418:42"/> ſo that I greatly feare that within ſhort time, it alſo will depart from vs, and by the commaundement of God goe vnto a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which ſhall (as the Theſſalonians did) receiue it, not as the word of men, but as it is in deede the worde of God. Well in the meane time, for the better auoyding and turning away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgements of God which hang ouer our heads, namely this preſent plague, whereby the Lorde in mercie hath viſited this Citie: I am to requeſt in the Lordes behalfe the right honorable, the Lord Maior of this Citie, and the reuerend Father the Biſhop, that they would ioyne together in gathering together y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, and calling a ſolemne aſſemblie,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.16.17.</note> and ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifiyng a generall and publicke faſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the commaundement of God, and the neceſſitie of this preſent time. This du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and chriſtian exerciſe is the rather to be done, leaſt our Engliſh Church for want thereof, may through ignorance iudge it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther altogether vnneceſſarie, or not much materiall. But if this cannot be obtained to be done in a publicke &amp; ſolemne maner, with all zeale and feruentnes in prayer and hearing the worde of God (which I
<pb facs="tcp:18418:42"/> moſt heartily wiſhe and deſire) then I doe admoniſhe euery one priuately, both to vſe this, and all other good meanes to turne from vs, and this Citie, all thoſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which our ſinnes haue moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deſerued. For it is not the cleane kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſweeping of our houſes and ſtreetes, that can driue away this fearefull meſſenger of Gods wrath, (albeit as I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue theſe lawfull ordinarie meanes: ſo I miſlike the deſperate tempting of God which I heare to be in ſome) but the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging &amp; ſweeping of our conſciences from all the ſtincking filthe and droſſe of ſinne, deliuereth from the feare and perill of all euill, and maketh vs pure and holy veſſels, meete for the holy Spirit of God to dwell in. If you will imploy all your labours, ſtudies, and cares hereunto, and offer vp this ſacrifice of praying, faſting, preaching, and thankes giuing, euen from the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto the euening, according to the example &amp; godly practiſes of our fathers which haue gone before vs: who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, deare brethren, yf the Lorde will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and repent and leaue a bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, euen the precious treaſure of his
<pb facs="tcp:18418:43"/> glorious Goſpel which now we haue, and the benefit of helth which as yet we want? But if this exhortation and requeſt ſhall fall to the ground, and bring forth no fruit, as commonly the woorde of God doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, (ſuch is the hardneſſe of our ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie heartes) then your ſinne lieth at the doore, and abideth, but my dutie, though in great weakeneſſe and feare, is diſcharged. Nowe therefore I commende vnto you, both this ſpeciall and ſingular woorke of publike and ſolemne faſting, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly woorkes, with faith, hope, loue, feare, and watchfulneſſe, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the ſyncere doing of the Fathers will: deſiryng and beſeeching you all to receiue, approue, and fulfill them vnto your liues end, that you may enter moſt ioyfully into the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Thus much by good occaſion I haue ſpoken, concerning the two ſortes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors: nowe I am to ſpeake by order, of the Apologie &amp; defence of the former ſort, for the auoyding of the finall ſentence of condemnation, conteyned in theſe wordes: <hi>Manie will ſay vnto me in that day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the text.</note> 
               <hi>Lorde, Lorde, haue we not by thy Name prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:43"/> and by thy Name caſt out deuils, and by thy Name done manie great workes?</hi> In theſe wordes Chriſt bringeth in not the vnlearned, but the learned and thoſe that ſeemed to be the chiefeſt, and beſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpell, reaſoning with him ſelfe, touching the matter of entring into the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">The defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the beſt ſort of fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ors.</note> They alledge for themſelues two principall and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie workes, not common vnto all, but almoſt proper and peculiar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iftes to the Miniſters and Apoſtles of Chriſt: that is to ſaye, preaching the word, ment here by prophecie, and working of myracles, vnderſtoode by caſting out deuils, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many and great workes. It may ſeeme ſtrange and marueylous in our eyes, that thoſe which can in trueth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for them ſelues theſe two workes, ſhoulde be ſecluded from the kingdome of heauen, ſeeing that of preachers it is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, that becauſe they turne many vnto righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Dan. 12 3.</note> they ſhal ſhine as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtarres for euer &amp; euer: of others, that whoſoeuer ſhal giue vnto any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples of Chriſt, in his name,<note place="margin">Mat 9.42. Mar. 9.41.</note> but a cuppe of colde water to drinke, that he ſhall not loſe his rewarde.
<pb facs="tcp:18418:44"/> Againe, ſeeing that of all workes of loue and compaſſion, theſe two in our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are without all compariſon the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: for what greater loue can any man ſhewe towardes the ſoule of his brother, then by preaching to deliuer it from the kingdome of darknes, and tranſlate it into the kingdome of light? or what greater loue can there be ſhewed towardes his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then to cure it from all infirmities, yea and that which is marueylous, to deliuer it from the poſſeſſion of deuils? notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we ſee by the anſwere of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, that theſe workes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al other which be of leſſe value, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient defences, either to alledge vnto Chriſt for the auoyding of the ſentence of death: or to perſwade our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that we are beloued of God, according to our former doctrine. For albeit they be neceſſarie for diuers and ſundry cauſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mencioned, yet they containe no part of that pure obedience, which by Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is wrought in all the true members of Chriſt. What then is that, which maketh preaching and all other workes acceptable vnto God, and profitable for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfort and
<pb facs="tcp:18418:44"/> ſaluation of the doer, ſeeyng the workes themſelues ſhalbe reiected? Surely to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in one word, it is the maner of doing: whereof we haue ſpoken before at large. In conſideration whereof, bleſſed Paule doeth iuſtifie his preaching, not becauſe he did preach, (for woe be vnto me, ſayth he,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16</note> if I preache not the Goſpell) but becauſe he obſerued the ryght maner &amp; order of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. The which maner,<note place="margin">The right maner of preaching reſpecteth vtterance, &amp; the inward affection. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24.</note> ſo farre forth as I can ſee and gather, concerneth either the vtterance of true doctrine, or the affection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde whence it procedeth. For the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, he witneſſeth that Chriſt ſent him to preache the Goſpell,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.17. &amp; 21.</note> not with wiſdome of wordes: yea that it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue. Agayne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.1.4. &amp; 5. verſ.</note> he reioyceth that he came not with excellencie of wordes, or of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhewing vnto the Corinthians the teſtimonie of God, and alſo that his worde and preaching ſtoode, not in the intycing ſpeache of mans wiſdome: but in playne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of the Spirit and power, that the faith of the hearers ſhoulde not be in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God. And to ſhewe in what wordes he ſpake the
<pb facs="tcp:18418:45"/> Goſpell of God, and who was the author &amp; teacher of them: he ſheweth playnly in an other place,<note place="margin">1. Co. 2.13.</note> ſaying, <hi>Which things alſo vve ſpeake, not in the wordes which mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome teacheth, but in the words which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpirituall things vvith ſpirituall things.</hi> For as the doctrine and foundation of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is altogether heauenly, and ſpirituall: ſo ought thoſe that be buylders thereupon, to buylde after a heauenly and ſpirituall maner: as the Apoſtle teacheth in another place, comparing this heauenly man to golde, ſiluer, and precious ſtones, and the contrary to tymber, haye, and ſtubble, in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">1. Co. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>If any man buylde vpon this foundation, golde, ſiluer, precious ſtones, tymber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>haye, or ſtubble, euery mans worke ſhalbe made manifeſt: for the day ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, becauſe it ſhall be reuealed by fire: and the fyre ſhall trye euery mans woorke of vvhat ſorte it is.</hi> Wherein we ſee howe neceſſarie a thing it is for vs, that be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and diuiders of the worde, not onely to looke vnto the foundation of our doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which is Chriſt: but alſo to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vtterance, becauſe that alſo muſt be
<pb facs="tcp:18418:45"/> tryed and examined by the holy Ghoſt: as golde, ſiluer, &amp;c. are tryed by the fire. Therefore Paule in great boldeneſſe, and authoritie ſpeaketh on this maner to the Corinthian preachers,<note place="margin">1. Co. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>But I vvill come to you ſhortly, if the Lorde vvill, and vvyll knovve, not the ſpeache of them vvhich are puffed vp, but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
               <note place="margin">20.</note> 
               <hi>For the kingdome of God is not in vvorde but in povver.</hi> Whereby as hee woulde condemne their ſpeache and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vtterance, which delyghted the eare, hauyng no power or ſtrength to weaken and vnlooſe the holde of ſinne and Satan in them: ſo he woulde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto them that maner of vtterance, which ſhoulde leaſt ſauour of carnall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and haue greateſt power to turne the hearts of the hearers vnto God: and as the Apoſtle doeth ſaye of himſelfe, that he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed no ſuch maner of teaching, neyther any flattering wordes, as it is in the fyrſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Theſſalonians:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.5</note> So he doeth moſt carefully commende and bequeath it vnto Timothie and Titus his two ſonnes in the fayth:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.13.</note> and in them to all other mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as a faithful treaſure for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edification
<pb facs="tcp:18418:46"/> of Chriſtes body, forbidding them to gyue heede vnto fables &amp; genealogies,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.7.</note> or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, and old wiues tales, vayne babblings, and oppoſitions of ſcience falſely ſo called, and contrarily commanding them to ſtaye ſuch things, to ſpeake and exhort with all authoritie, &amp; to ſtudie to ſhewe themſelues approued to God, and workemen that need not be aſhamed, and finally to deuide the word aright. This kinde of preaching tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vttering of the worde, diligently obſerued of Paule, and faithfully commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his ſchollers, ought with great care and diligence to be obſerued of all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God: that the faith of the hearers may ſtande in the power of the Spirit and trueth, &amp; not in the weakenes of the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wordes of mans wiſedome. But alas, who preacheth thus? nay who doeth not iudge this kinde of preaching to be voyde of learning, diſcretion, &amp; wiſdome? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many doe ſtuffe their ſermons with newe deuiſed words, and affected ſpeaches of vanitie, not being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with the words which the holy Ghoſt teacheth. Many with vnneceſſary ſentences, prouerbes, ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and ſtories collected out of the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb facs="tcp:18418:46"/> of prophane men: many with curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affected figures, with Latine, Greeke, and Hebrewe ſentences, without any iuſt occaſion offered by their texte, with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of humane authorities, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of men, in whom there can be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d neither certaine rule of trueth, neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in iudgement, and therfore very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte to be admitted into that place as ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, wheras the fearefull &amp; mighty voyce of God, hath ſtraightly charged all people to heare his welbeloued Sonne, ſaying, This is my welbeloued So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, heare him. Many with ſtagelike geſtures, curious pronunciation, and ſuch other actions that are very vnſeemely for thoſe men, which haue taken vpon them before God and his Angels, to preach and publiſh vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Goſpel of Chriſt crucified. I would to God that all the miniſters of this lande, in this poynt could put on this affection of S. Paule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> fully to purpoſe with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to knowe nothing amongeſt their hearers, ſaue Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified. So we ſhoulde not onely caſt aſide this vayne, corrupt, &amp; vnprofitable maner of diuiding the worde of trueth: but alſo baniſhe out of
<pb facs="tcp:18418:47"/> our heartes the deſire of all ſuch popular prayſe, and commendation. But to let paſſe the vtterance of ſpeache, lette vs come to the affection of the minde: the generall diſpoſition whereof I touched briefely before, to witte, that we ſhoulde laye aſide all deſire of ſhewe of humane knowledge, and purpoſe onely to reioyce in the knowledge of Chriſt crucified: the particular affections, required to make our prophecying or preaching accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God, as they are commaunded in diuers and ſundrie places of the worde: ſo the Apoſtle reioyceth, that he obſerued in a good conſcience this heauenly kinde of preaching. In the firſt chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of Peter, the holie Ghoſt commendeth vnto the miniſters of Chriſt, an earneſt care, a willing heart, a ready minde, a zealous deſyre to become en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples to their flockes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2.</note> ſaying, <hi>Feede the flocke of God vvhich dependeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, caryng for it not by conſtraynt, but willingly: not for fylthie lucre, but of a readie mynde:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.</note> 
               <hi>not as though you vvere lordes of Gods heritage, but that yee may bee enſamples to the flocke.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18418:47"/> Alſo our Sauiour Chriſt the chiefe ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde of the flocke, as appeareth in the tenth of Matth. Goſpell,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.</note> ſending out his Diſciples to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael, chargeth them wholly to depende vpon him, to gyue freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of filthie lucre, to feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the execution of their office, to be fully reſolued in their mindes to loſe their lyues for his ſake: finally to keepe them ſelues in all reſpects pure, and innocent as doues. Whereunto agreeth that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Paule to Timothie, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ordination of Miniſters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he teacheth, that euery miniſter ought to be watchefull, ſober, modeſt, louers, harborous, a louer of goodneſſe, wyſe, ryghteous, holy, temperate, and vnrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable. So that by theſe precepts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes it euidently appeareth, with what care of the flocke, willingneſſe, and readines of minde, deſire by example to edifie, boldenes of heart, confidence in God, loue of Chriſt and his ſheepe: with what full purpoſe with loſſe of lyfe to perſeuer vnto the ende, and laſtly with what contempte of all worldly prayſe,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:48"/> and with what zeale of Gods glorie, euery miniſter ought to approue his miniſterie vnto Chriſt, &amp; the conſciences of his flock. But if we wyll ſee theſe preceptes put in vre and practiſe, let vs diligently marke the lyfe and conuerſation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, eſpecially of Saint Paule: (who as he was the chiefeſt in worke, ſo the playneſt in declaration hereof,) and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare in euery particular his behauiour in the execution of his miniſterie, with ours. He ſayeth,<note place="margin">1. Co. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Though I preache the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, I haue nothing to reioyce of: for neceſsitie is layde vpon mee, and vvoe is vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">17.</note> 
               <hi>if I preache not the Goſpell. For if I doe it vvyllingly, I haue a revvarde: but if I doe it agaynſt my vvyll, notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the diſpenſation is committed vnto mee.</hi> But which of vs doeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and is glad, when he hath preached a fewe ſermons with lyking and prayſe of mortall men? What dumme dogge doeth terrifie his owne heart from ſinne, with this woe agaynſt him ſelfe for not prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell? or who doeth not for lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, feare, and prayſe of men, rather then willingly &amp; of a ready mind, feed the poore
<pb facs="tcp:18418:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> flocke of Chriſt? Paul, though he was free from all men,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9 19. &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet he made him ſelfe ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto all, that he might winne the more: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iewe he became a Iewe, to them that were vnder the lawe, as though he were vnder the lawe, to the weake he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as weake, and in deede he was made all things to all men, for the Goſpels ſake, that he might be partaker thereof. But where is that Miniſter amongſt vs, which through loue humbleth him ſelfe, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infirmities of ignorance, lacke of knowledge, wiſdome, and diſcretion in his flocke and felow brethren? Nay which of vs with Paul beateth downe his bodie,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note> and bringeth it into ſubiection, leſt in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to others he him ſelf become a caſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? the Lord pardon vs this our offence. For I feare me, the care we haue of our mortall bodies, farre ſurmounteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> care we haue of the ſaluation of our ſelues, or of our brethren.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.10 33.</note> Paul did pleaſe all men in all thinges, not ſeeking his owne profit, but the profit of many, that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but as for vs, though many I graunt doe pleaſe all men in all thinges, yet they ſeeke their owne profit and gaine, not the
<pb facs="tcp:18418:49"/> profite of any one that he might be ſaued. For in deede they make marchandize of the worde of God, they are couered with the clokes of ſhame, and walke in crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they handle the worde of GOD deceytfullye, preaching them ſelues and not Chriſte Ieſus the Lorde, nor them ſelues the ſeruantes of his people: and that which is moſt lamentable of all, they gyue great and iuſt occaſion, why the miniſterie of reconciliation ſhoulde bee euill ſpoken of and deſpyſed.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.1.2.</note> Contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Paule, he ſpake of Chriſte as of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, as of God in the ſight of God, he caſt of the clokes of ſhame, and walked in declaration of the trueth: he approoued himſelfe to euery mans conſcience in the ſight of GOD, he preached Chriſt Ieſus the Lorde, himſelfe a ſeruant for Ieſus ſake: and to conclude, he gaue no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of offence in any thing, but in all things approued himſelfe as the miniſter of God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.7.</note> by the worde of Trueth and by the power of God. Seeing therefore many of vs be fallen away from our firſt loue, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer zeale, and haue imbraced this preſent worlde, which (yf the Lorde be not more
<pb facs="tcp:18418:49"/> mercifull) will choke in vs all the graces of GOD: we had neede to looke vnto our ſelues betimes, and to frame our ſelues according to the example of this bleſſed Apoſtle, in the carefull and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere diſpenſation of our miniſterie, leaſt our preaching bee (though profitable to others) yet damnable to our ſelues. Moreouer Paule was gentle towardes his flocke,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.7 &amp;. 11.</note> as a Nurſe cheriſheth her children, exhorting and beſeeching them as a father, teaching openly,<note place="margin">Act. 20.20.</note> and through euery houſe, keeping nothing backe that was profitable, but ſhewing vnto them all the counſell of God: and to ſhutte vp all in one worde, he was verie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and wylling to deale vnto them,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.8</note> not the Goſpell of God onely: but alſo his owne ſoule becauſe they were deare vnto him. Beholde here in Paule, as in a moſt cleare glaſſe, a perfect paterne of a good and faythfull ſeruant of God: and on the other ſide our miſerable imperfections, and ſinfull degenerating from the ſame. This kinde of preaching is that onely wherein we may reioyce, which is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, profitable to his Church,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:50"/> comfortable to the ſpeaker. This is that true and perfect paterne of preaching, which Paul committed to Timothie, both in reſpect of the vtterance, and of the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the minde, which he chargeth to be kept and obſerued, that he might be an example to them that beleeue, in worde, in conuerſation, in loue, in ſpirit, in faith and in purenes,<note place="margin">2. Timo. 1.13.</note> ſaying, <hi>Keepe the true paterne of the wholeſome words, which thou haſt heard of me in fayth, and loue which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">14</note> 
               <hi>That worthy thing which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to thee, keepe through the holy Ghoſt, vvhich dvvelleth in vs.</hi> And to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Aboue all thinges ſhevve thy ſelfe an example of good vvorkes, vvith vncorrupt doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8</note> 
               <hi>vvith the vvholeſome vvoorde vvhich cannot be reproued.</hi> This is that which though we alledge in the laſt daye for our ſelues, we ſhal not be diſliked or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. But alas our kinde and maner of preaching, whether we regarde the vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſpeach, or affection of our hearts, doth farre differ from this, nay it is almoſt cleane contrary to it: for it giueth no life to thoſe which are dead in ſinne, it hath no power to ſtrike in ſunder, or to vnlooſe the
<pb facs="tcp:18418:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> holde of ſinne, no ſharpeneſſe to cutte a ſunder the cordes of wickedneſſe, it can not enter to the diuiding a ſunder of the ſoule and ſpirit, the ioyntes and the marowe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it diſcerne betweene the thoughts and intentes of the heart: and why? our woordes are of our owne making, and not ſuch as the Spirit of God teacheth: our matter for the moſt part is the deuiſes of men, the diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our hearts prophane, worldly and carnall, our intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to get honour, and worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments. No maruayle therefore though our labours be curſed, and not bleſſed, and wee our ſelues in the day of iudgement be reiected: for as I haue taught before, it is not the woorke done, but the maner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that pleaſeth our heauenly Father. So that thoſe onely which preach the worde in faith, hope, loue, feare, and all maner of watchfulneſſe, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, being ready as to deale vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people the Goſpel of God, ſo alſo if neceſſitie require, their owne liues for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmation of their flocke: thoſe I ſay only ſhall reape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite of their labours, with great ioye and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euen eternall lyfe, wherein they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18418:51"/> ſhine as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtarres of heauen. As for others, who haue in preaching the worde ſought themſelues, their owne praiſe and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, hauing litle or no care of Gods heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that it might be ſaued: (of which ſort be thoſe whereof I haue already ſpoken a litle before) though they ſay in the day of iudgement, Lorde, Lord, haue we not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied in thy Name, yet they ſhalbe ſent away to their owne place of puniſhment, as workers of iniquitie. If then the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde worke of preaching, which is ſo profitable vnto the Church for the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of ſoules, ſhalbe reiected, being ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the pure maner: who dare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge caſting out of deuils, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of great miracles which onely apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the ſafety of body? Let not therfore the Papiſts reioyce, though they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to confirme euery point of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a great miracle (whereas in deede they are not, except we will iudge their vaine forged miracles to be done by the finger of God:) for yf theſe myracles be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the true maner of doing the Fathers will, the dooers themſelues are but workers of iniquitie, as Chriſt moſt
<pb facs="tcp:18418:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> truely termeth them in the verſe follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing: and therefore ſo farre from being iuſtified by theſe, or any other workes of charitie, being ſeparated from the true maner of doing, that thei ſhalbe vnto them ſufficient matter of condemnacion. Well, it is neither preaching, nor working of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, that can deliuer the preacher or any other from the ſentence of death in that day, neither any other, which proceedeth not from the right maner of doing the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will. But in aſmuch as the wicked ones, which beare the ſhewe of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, may both in the outwarde worke, and in a certaine maner of doing, come verie nere vnto the acceptable doing of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will, which in appearance they do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much reſemble: it ſhalbe verie profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſerch a litle deeper,<note place="margin">How nere the wicked may come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly.</note> if by any meanes we can finde how many, and what be thoſe gifts which the wicked, ouer and beſides theſe, may alledge for themſelues, becauſe thei are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to them with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly. It is certain by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of our ſauiour Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel of Matthew, Mark &amp; Luke,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.20. Mar. 4.15. Luk. 8.11.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wicked may willingly heare, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ioyfully receyue, &amp; profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde,
<pb facs="tcp:18418:52"/> yea indure for a ſeaſon, &amp; falſely perſwade them ſelues to beleeue. So is it witneſſed of Simon Magus, that he hearde Philip preaching, vnderſtood him, ioyfully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his doctrine, and that he beleeued, was baptized, and continued with Philippe: in theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Act. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>Then Simon him ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued alſo, and vvas baptized, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vvith Philippe, and vvondered vvhen he ſavve the ſignes and great miracles that vvere done.</hi> Notwithſtanding Peter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to his face, that he had no parte nor fellowſhippe in that buſineſſe: becauſe his heart was not ryght in the ſyght of God, but full of gall and bitterneſſe, and that he was in the bonde of iniquitie. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer they may relieue and ſuccour, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and highly eſteeme of the miniſters of Chriſt, thinking nothing to deare for them: So Paule witneſſeth of the Galatians, ſaying,<note place="margin">Gala. 4.14.15.16.20.</note> 
               <hi>And the triall of me which was in my fleſhe, ye diſpiſed not, neither abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: but ye receiued me as an angel of god, yea as Chriſte Ieſus. What was then your felicity? for I beare you record, that if it had bin poſſible, you would haue plucked out your ovvn eyes, &amp; haue giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18418:52"/> Yet they afterwarde, as it followeth in the ſame place, eſteemed him as an enemie, in ſomuch as he ſayeth he doubted of them. Againe, they may abſtayne from euill, and do the outward works of charitie,<note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> wherby they ſeeme very ryghteous vnto men, as did the Scribes &amp; Phariſes: they may giue their goods and landes vnto the church,<note place="margin">1. Co. 13.3. Acts. 5.1.2.</note> as did Ananias and Saphira: they may bee lightned with the knowledge of the trueth, taſte of the heauenly gift &amp; the good worde of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.</note> and the powers of the worlde to come, and be made partakers of the holie Ghoſt, and yet fall from the grace recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as it is in the 6. and 10. chap. to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes: Finally, they may ſuffer baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and perſecution for the outward profeſſion of the trueth, yea they may do all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward workes in ſeruing of God, &amp; helping their neyghbour, which the godly doe: but when the queſtion ſhall be demaunded of Chriſt, who in deede and in trueth is his brother, ſiſter, and mother, he wil anſwere, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhal do my fathers vvill vvhich is in heauen, the ſame is my brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.50</note> 
               <hi>ſiſter &amp; mother.</hi> Now ſeeing how farre ſinners and vngodly men may reſemble the deare
<pb facs="tcp:18418:53"/> children of God, &amp; yet be voyde of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of regeneration: let vs looke into our ſelues, into our hearts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, &amp; whole maner of our life, that we may ſee &amp; know in all our actions, wherin we differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked, &amp; how we do our Fathers wil: for it behoueth euery true Chriſtian, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of Chriſt, to do all theſe works before mencioned, in conſtant faith, in ſure hope, in pure loue, in reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feare, in great care &amp; ſtudy to pleaſe God, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> zeale of gods glory, &amp; tender loue of his brethren, with ioye in the holy Ghoſt, with a reſolued pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe without wearines &amp; fainting to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vnto the end, knowing that thoſe only ſhalbe bleſſed, which ſhal continue vnto the ende. This is our liuing, holy, &amp; acceptable ſacrifice vnto God, &amp; this onely is our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſeruing of him: wherin whoſoeuer continueth, ſhal neuer periſh, but be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life. If we wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this, though we heare often, knowe much, ſpeake neuer ſo wel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel, make neuer ſo much of preachers, &amp; reioyce for a time in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth: yet I ſay, if this faith, hope, loue, feare and watchfulnes be abſent, we are baſtardes &amp; no children, hypocrites, no Chriſtians, for
<pb facs="tcp:18418:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> whome remaineth nothing, but a fearefull looking for of iudgement and violent fire, which ſhal deuour al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſaries of God and his trueth. I ſpeake this not to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage any, or to driue the weake conſciences into diſtruſt: but to awake the ſlouthfull, &amp; to terrifie the proude, ſecure, &amp; preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; alſo to ſtir vs al vp to a more vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t care in working our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How neceſſary this is to be preached &amp; vrged, the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; error of many, the want of loue &amp; feare of God in this land &amp; citie, doth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently witnes. I therfore, to make an end of this matter, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende this doctrine from Ieſus vnto you all, beſeeching you for the mercies of God, to receyue it into your ſoules, to beleeue it in heart, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend it in word, diligently to practiſe it in life, &amp; with al your ſtrength &amp; might to maintaine and defende it, againſt all aduerſarie power of Satan and his miniſters.</p>
            <p>The anſwere of Chriſt in the verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, containeth two points.<note place="margin">The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of Chriſt.</note> Firſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth theſe men to be his ſeruants: Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily he ſendeth them awaye, &amp; baniſheth them for euer out of his preſence, ſaying, <hi>And then I will profeſſe to them, I neuer
<pb facs="tcp:18418:54"/> knew you:</hi> meaning by knowing, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging. For the Greeke worde (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſignifieth, not onely a bare knowledge of a thyng, but an acceptation or approouing, which we call acknowledging, ſo that it is all one as if he ſhoulde ſay, Albeit you haue by prophecying, &amp; working miracles, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed your ſelues to be my ſeruants, &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me Lorde and Maſter: yet becauſe you did not thoſe things which I commanded you, I did neuer acknowledge you to be my ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; now I do profeſſe vnto you the ſame. O what a terror, and griefe of heart is this, to heare the Sauiour of the world, in whom onely there is hope of mercie and lyfe, to denie and openly profeſſe, that hee neuer acknowledged vs to be his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? The ſeruaunt to be forſaken of his louing Maſter, the ſubiect of his godly Prince, the childe of his naturall parents, the wyfe of her deare huſband, is matter of vntolerable griefe and deadly ſorow: But for a man to be forſaken of the Redeemer of mankinde, and that openly in the preſence of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, without hope of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation, whoſe heart doeth not quite fayle him, and melte away, euen to thinke therof? O then what
<pb facs="tcp:18418:54"/> a hell of tormentes ſhall it be to the ſoule, eternally to feele it? Go to then, you yong and deſperate ruffians, you carnall &amp; licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Proteſtantes, reioyce in your youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wanton pleaſures, cheare your hearts in the dayes of your vanitie, walke in the wayes of your owne luſtes, enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, deſpiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; wiſdome, deuiſe your wittie prouerbs againſt the iuſt, deride and mocke at the wayes of the godly, ſuffer not your conſciences to accuſe you, caſt awaye the feare of Gods wrath out of your hearts, &amp; withdraw no pleaſures from your mindes: yet know this for a certaintie, that God wil bring you, and euery worke to iudgement, with euery ſecret thing whether it be good or euill: at what time you ſhal knowe and feele, by miſerable experience, what it is to heare this voyce of Chriſt, <hi>Depart from me ye vvorkers of iniquitie.</hi> As this deniall of Chriſt ſhal be moſt terrible vnto the curſed company of al reprobates, ſo it ſhalbe moſt ioyful to the litle flocke of Gods heritage: For they ſhall not onely reioyce, in that God ſhall be glorified in the deſtruction of all their enemies: but eſpecially in that
<pb facs="tcp:18418:55"/> they ſhalbe acknowledged of Chriſt, as his faithfull ſeruants and deare brethren, and be aduaunced into the inheritance of his Fathers kyngdome, in compariſon of which honour, all the glory and pompe of the earth, is nothing els but lotheſome beggery.</p>
            <p>Touching the ſeconde poynt of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, we are to note and obſerue firſt, the ſending of them away, &amp; the reaſon therof. For the firſt he ſayeth, <hi>Depart from mee,</hi> ſignifying thereby, that although they in outwarde ſhewe and profeſſion ſeemed to gather with Chriſt, as his ſeruantes, and therefore were accompted amongeſt the nomber of Gods elect: Yet nowe when all mens heartes and ſecrete thoughtes are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and reuealed, eyther to their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe deſtruction, or eternal comfort, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the godly ſhall eaſily be diſcerned from the vngodly: then euen preachers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, woorkers of miracles, and all other diſſembling profeſſours of the Goſpel, ſhal heare with great ſorowe and griefe, this finall ſentence of death and damnation, <hi>Depart from mee.</hi> If any man do aſke me whyther they ſhall goe from Chriſt, or
<pb facs="tcp:18418:55"/> where they ſhall abyde out of his preſence, I anſwere briefely, into euerlaſting fire: as our Sauiour Chriſt him ſelfe doeth wytneſſe in the 25. of Matthewe, ſaying, <hi>Depart from mee yee curſed into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fyre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.41</note> 
               <hi>vvhich is prepared for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his angelles.</hi> Yf then, deere bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, preachers of the Goſpell, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of miracles ſhall be throwen from the preſence of God into vtter darkenes, as woorkers of iniquitie, for want of the true maner of doyng the Fathers wyll: O Lorde, what ſhall become of all thoſe Miniſters, which receyuing temporall things of the people of God redeemed by the blood of Chriſt, doe in the hardneſſe of their heartes refuſe to miniſter vnto them ſpirituall, and to feede them with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly foode of the worde vnto eternall lyfe? But becauſe no admonition can moue them to repentance, &amp; reformation of this haynous offence agaynſt God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I leaue them to anſwere for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto Chriſt, at the dreadfull daye of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: at what time I feare me, that as they haue bene dum in this life, concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſounding out of the mighty word of god:
<pb facs="tcp:18418:56"/> ſo they wyll be altogether dumme and ſpeachleſſe, when Chriſt ſhal cal for a wiſe, diligent and watchefull diſcharge of that ſtewardſhip which they haue vſurped, and horribly abuſed in the Church of God. As for Atheiſts, Idolaters, blaſphemers, ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, deſpiſers of magiſtracie, murtherers, adulterers, fornicators, oppreſſors, vſurers, and ſuch like abominable ſinners, how can they eſcape the vengeance and iuſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their rewarde, ſeeyng that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the worde, and woorkers of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſhall be throwen into the chaynes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting darkenes? O that men woulde ſeriouſly conſider this, and turne vnto the Lorde with all their hearts and ſoules, in this acceptable time of grace: for euen now wiſdome cryeth without, the ſounde of the Goſpell is heard in our temples: nowe is the time of peace, nowe is the day of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: To day if you will heare the ioyfull voyce of Chriſt, harden not your heartes with the wicked of this worlde: but ceaſe from your owne workes, and doe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will which is in heauen. So doyng, the God of peace ſhal ſanctifie you through out, and keepe your whole ſpirit, ſoule, and
<pb facs="tcp:18418:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> bodie blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. The reaſon of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull departure is, for that in preaching, caſting out deuils, and working miracles, they wrought and committed iniquitie: for ſo it is ſayd, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquitie.</hi> Not that they did vnlawfull workes, but becauſe they did lawful things vnlawfully: for albeit they preached and wrought miracles (both which did auaile much to the edification of the Church) yet in regard of the corrupt maner of doing, Chriſt calleth them, <hi>Workers of iniquitie.</hi> This doctrine condemneth all men which do lawfull thinges vnlawfully: how much more thoſe which doe vnlawfull thinges, though they haue neuer ſo great a ſhewe of godlyneſſe? Good workes, I confeſſe, muſt be done: but ſuch onely are good, which God hath commaunded in his word, not ſuch as men by worldly wiſdome haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed: of which ſort are running on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the dumme and ſenſeleſſe images, doing of penance at the prieſtes appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an infinite nomber of the ſame, not onely in that Popiſh religion, but alſo in all humaine and voluntarie ſeruice. For
<pb facs="tcp:18418:57"/> they haue not ſo much as a ſhewe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement out of the word, and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God: as maye eaſily appeare to him, that hath but once in all his life read ouer the Bible. Here then we ſee, how eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man maye pleaſe and diſpleaſe God: pleaſe, if he doe that which is commaunded of God, after that maner he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it: diſpleaſe, if he doe any thing either not commanded, but deuiſed of man: or do the thing commaunded, after an vnlawfull maner. In conſideration whereof, all thoſe that be out of the Church, are iuſtly termed workers of iniquitie, for the which at the day of Iudgement they ſhalbe eternallye condemned. Contrarily, thoſe which are in and of the Church, which is the myſtical bodie of Chriſt, becauſe they doe workes commaunded after an vpright and ſincere maner, Chriſt doth iuſtly call them, Doers of his Fathers will: to whom by promiſe, not by deſert, belongeth the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen, and euerlaſting happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore to make an ende, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche you, for the loue that you beare to your owne ſaluation, as though Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:18418:57"/> ſhould beſeeche you by me, to abhorre and eſchewe the curſed behauiour of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling profeſſours, to embrace and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize the vpright and ſyncere maner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fathers will, to contend and ſtriue to enter in at the narrow gate of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, to flie al apparance of euil, to abound plentifully in all good workes, keeping faith, hope, loue, feare, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe without wearyneſſe and faynting, euen vntill the laſt moment of lyfe: that Chriſte which is our lyfe may receyue vs into eternall lyfe, and immortall glorie. This is my humble petition vnto you, and my daylie prayer for all the Saintes and electe of GOD: that we being all, moſt perfectly by the holie Ghoſt, and fayth, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and incorporated into Chriſte (as the members of the body into the head) might be partakers of the felowſhippe of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, together with his and our Father, and al the holy companie of Angels, in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome of all happyneſſe and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. Nowe I for my part aſſuredly hope, and perſwade my ſelfe, that all thoſe that loue the comming of Ieſus Chriſt, will lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly receiue this my petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after:
<pb facs="tcp:18418:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> And I conſtantly beleeue, that our moſt mercifull Father wil heare my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this my requeſt, to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting prayſe of his mercie, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall comfort of his Churche. To him therefore with his Sonne, &amp; the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, three perſons and one immortall and euerliuing GOD, be all praiſe, power, glorie and thankeſgiuing for euer &amp; euer, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes Maieſtie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:58"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:59"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18418:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
